[
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 1,
    "Question": "When calculating an answer what is the appropriate number of significant figures",
    "Answer": "The same as the value in the question with least number of significant figures."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 2,
    "Question": "What six base units of the SI system are used in A Level Physics?",
    "Answer": "metre, kilogram, second, Ampere, Kelvin, Mole"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 3,
    "Question": "What six base quantities of the SI system are used in A Level Physics?",
    "Answer": "length, mass,  time, electric current, absolute temperature, amount of substance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 4,
    "Question": "In an experiment you plot v^2 against s. If the equation for the straight line is v^2-U^2 = 2as state what can be found from the gradient and the y intercept",
    "Answer": "Y intersept = u^2  and gradient = 2a"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 5,
    "Question": "In an experiment you plot V against I. If the equation for the straight line is E = V - Ir state what the gradient and y intercept represents",
    "Answer": "Y intercept = E and gradient = -r"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 6,
    "Question": "How can you convert from kN to N?",
    "Answer": "x 1000"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 7,
    "Question": "What are the standard units for mass?",
    "Answer": "kg"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 8,
    "Question": "How can you convert from MHz to Hz",
    "Answer": "x 1000000 (1x10^6)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 9,
    "Question": "How can you convert from GJ (giga joules) to J",
    "Answer": "1 x 10^9"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 10,
    "Question": "How can you convert from TA (tera amps) to A",
    "Answer": "1 x 10^12"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 11,
    "Question": "How can you convert from cm to m",
    "Answer": "Divide by 100"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 12,
    "Question": "How can you convert form mm to m",
    "Answer": "Divide by 1000 (1 x 10^-3)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 13,
    "Question": "How can you convert from micrometeres to meters",
    "Answer": "divide by 1000000 (1x10^-6)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 14,
    "Question": "How can you convert form nm to m",
    "Answer": "1 x 10^-9"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 15,
    "Question": "How can you convert form pm (picometers) to m",
    "Answer": "1 x 10^-12"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 16,
    "Question": "What is 1m² in mm²?",
    "Answer": "10⁶mm²"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 17,
    "Question": "What is 1m³ in cm³?",
    "Answer": "10⁶cm³"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 18,
    "Question": "What is 1km² in m²?",
    "Answer": "1x10⁶m²"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 19,
    "Question": "What is 1cm³ in mm³?",
    "Answer": "10³mm³"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 20,
    "Question": "There are 10²⁴ free charge carriers per m³ of a material. How many are there per mm³?",
    "Answer": "10¹⁵"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 21,
    "Question": "10⁶ particles strike each mm² of a surface per second. How many strike 1m² of the surface per second?",
    "Answer": "10¹²"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 22,
    "Question": "If there is 1 particle per mm³, how many are there per m³?",
    "Answer": "10⁹"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 23,
    "Question": "Water has a density of 1000 kgm⁻³. What is this in kgcm⁻³?",
    "Answer": "10⁻³"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 24,
    "Question": "Water has a density of 1000 kgm⁻³. What is this in gcm⁻³?",
    "Answer": "1"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 25,
    "Question": "What is a control variable?",
    "Answer": "Something that must be kept constant to prevent it affecting the dependent variable"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 26,
    "Question": "What is meant by the repeatability of results?",
    "Answer": "Similar results would be obtained from repeats of the same measurement from the same experimental set up."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 27,
    "Question": "What is meant by the reproducibility of results",
    "Answer": "Similar results would be obtained from repeats by different people with different equipment."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 28,
    "Question": "How can you ensure a metre rule is held vertically?",
    "Answer": "Use a plumb line,  set square or spirit level"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 29,
    "Question": "How do you avoid parallax error?",
    "Answer": "Ensure eye, object and scale are all in line with each other OR ensure object and scale are directly adjacent to each other"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 30,
    "Question": "What is meant by the term random error?",
    "Answer": "Errors that cause the measurement to vary in unpredictable ways."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 31,
    "Question": "What is a systematic error?",
    "Answer": "An error that causes the measurements to differ from the true value by a consistent amount."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 32,
    "Question": "What is a zero error?",
    "Answer": "An error that occurs due to the measuring instrument reading a non-zero reading when the measured quantity is zero."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 33,
    "Question": "What is meant by the accuracy of a result?",
    "Answer": "How close a measurement is to the 'true' or accepted value"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 34,
    "Question": "What is meant by the precision of results?",
    "Answer": "How close repeated measurements are to each other."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 35,
    "Question": "What is meant by the resolution of a measuring instrument?",
    "Answer": "The smallest change in quantity that can be measured."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 36,
    "Question": "What determines the resolution when using a multimeter?",
    "Answer": "The scale selected."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 37,
    "Question": "What is the resolution of a metre rule?",
    "Answer": "1mm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 38,
    "Question": "What is the resolution of vernier callipers?",
    "Answer": "0.1mm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 39,
    "Question": "What is the resolution of a micrometre",
    "Answer": "0.01mm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 40,
    "Question": "How do you find the absolute uncertainty from repeated readings?",
    "Answer": "± ½ the range of the repeats"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 41,
    "Question": "How do you estimate uncertainty when repeated results are identical?",
    "Answer": "± ½ the resolution of the instrument"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 42,
    "Question": "How do you calculate percentage uncertainty?",
    "Answer": "(Absolute uncertainty ÷ 'calculated OR measured' value) × 100"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 43,
    "Question": "What do you do to the uncertainties when quantities are added or subtracted?",
    "Answer": "The absolute uncertainties are added together"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 44,
    "Question": "What do you do to the uncertainties when quantities are multiplied or divided?",
    "Answer": "The percentage uncertainties are added together"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 45,
    "Question": "What do you do to the uncertainties when a quantity is raised to a power?",
    "Answer": "The percentage uncertainty is multiplied by that power"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 46,
    "Question": "How do you find the uncertainty in a gradient?",
    "Answer": "± (gradient of the line of best fit − gradient of the line of worst fit)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 47,
    "Question": "What is a line of worst fit?",
    "Answer": "The steepest or shallowest line that passes through the error bars."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Sub-topic": "Measurements and their errors ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 1,
    "No.": 48,
    "Question": "What are error bars?",
    "Answer": "Lines to show the range of the absolute uncertainty of each data point on a graph"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 49,
    "Question": "Describe the nuclear model of the atom",
    "Answer": "A positive nucleus containing protons and neutrons with electrons found in shells orbiting the nucleus"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 50,
    "Question": "State the relative charge of all sub atomic particles",
    "Answer": "Proton +1, Neutron 0, Electron -1"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 51,
    "Question": "State the relative masses of all sub atomic particles",
    "Answer": "Proton 1, Neutron 1, Electron almost 0 (1/1840)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 52,
    "Question": "How can you calculate the septic charge? Giving all units",
    "Answer": "Specific charge (C/kg) = charge (C) / mass (kg)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 53,
    "Question": "Charge/mass =",
    "Answer": "Specific charge"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 54,
    "Question": "Define atomic (proton number)",
    "Answer": "The number of protons in a nucleus = the number of electrons for an uncharged atom"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 55,
    "Question": "Define nucleon number",
    "Answer": "The number of nucleons (protons + neutrons)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 56,
    "Question": "An element with the same number of protons but a different number of neutrons",
    "Answer": "An isotope"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 57,
    "Question": "Define an isotope",
    "Answer": "An isotope is the same element with the same number of protons but different number of neutrons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 58,
    "Question": "Why is the strong nuclear force important?",
    "Answer": "It keeps nucleus stable"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 59,
    "Question": "Sketch a graph of force against separation for the strong nuclear force",
    "Answer": "Must be attractive and repulsive at different distance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 60,
    "Question": "When is the strong nuclear force attractive",
    "Answer": "Between 0.5 and 3 fm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 61,
    "Question": "When is the strong nuclear force repulsive",
    "Answer": "A distances closer than 0.5 fm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 62,
    "Question": "Describe some properties of the strong nuclear force",
    "Answer": "Very strong - overcomes repulsion between positive protons, Very short range - only acts between adjacent nucleons, Acts on any nucleon (proton or neutron) and is independent of charge, Can be attractive or repulsive"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 63,
    "Question": "How does the strong nuclear force cause particles to be in equilibrium",
    "Answer": "Increase in nucleon separation leads to an attractive force. Decrease in nucleon separation leads to a repulsive force In both situations, force will return nucleons back to equilibrium position."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 64,
    "Question": "What are the three types of radioactive decay?",
    "Answer": "Alpha, Beta, Gamma"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 65,
    "Question": "Describe an alpha particle",
    "Answer": "2 protons and 2 neutrons or a Helium nucleus"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 66,
    "Question": "State the ionizing ability of an alpha particle",
    "Answer": "Highly"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 67,
    "Question": "State the relative mass and charge of an alpha particle.",
    "Answer": "Mass = 4 Charge = +2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 68,
    "Question": "State what can stop an alpha particle",
    "Answer": "10 cm air, skin or paper"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 69,
    "Question": "Describe a beta particle",
    "Answer": "fast moving electron ejected from the nucleus"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 70,
    "Question": "State the relative mass and charge of a beta particle?",
    "Answer": "Mass almost 0 Charge = -1"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 71,
    "Question": "State the ionizing ability of a beta particle?",
    "Answer": "Moderately ionizing"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 72,
    "Question": "State what can be used to stop a beta particle?",
    "Answer": "A few mm's of aluminium"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 73,
    "Question": "Describe a gamma wave",
    "Answer": "Electromagnetic wave that moves at the speed of light through a vacuum by cm's lead or m's of concrete"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 74,
    "Question": "State the relative mass and charge of a gamma wave.",
    "Answer": "Mass = 0 Charge = 0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 75,
    "Question": "State the ionizing ability of a gamma wave",
    "Answer": "Very weakly ionizing"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 76,
    "Question": "State how gamma waves can be reduced",
    "Answer": "A few cm's of lead"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 77,
    "Question": "Describe the changes that take place in beta decay",
    "Answer": "A neutron decays into a proton creating the beta particle and an electron antineutrino. For a neutron to decay into a proton a down quark decays into a up quark"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 78,
    "Question": "Describe the evidence that neutrinos exist",
    "Answer": "Experimental data shows that as a beta particle is emitted in beta decay it will have a range of energies from nearly zero up to a maximum. All decays must have the same energy.(conservation of energy). The total energy and momentum of the beta particle and recoiling nucleus was not constant. Energy has to be conserved Wolfgang  predicted a particle that could carry away the extra energy/momentum so they would be conserved. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 79,
    "Question": "Describe the changes that take place in positron emission",
    "Answer": "A proton decays into a neutron creating the positron and an electron neutrino. For a proton to decay into a neutron a up quark decays into a down quark."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 80,
    "Question": "Why does an antineutrino need to be released during beta decay?",
    "Answer": "To conserve, energy, momentum and lepton number"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 81,
    "Question": "Define a fundamental particle",
    "Answer": "Fundamental particles cannot be divided into other particles. They have no internal structure."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 82,
    "Question": "Give some examples of fundamental particles",
    "Answer": "Electron, neutrino, all quarks"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 83,
    "Question": "What are the 6 types of quark",
    "Answer": "Up, down, strange, charm, top, bottom"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 84,
    "Question": "What is the quark structure of a proton?",
    "Answer": "u u d "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 85,
    "Question": "What is the quark structure of a neutron?",
    "Answer": "u d d "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 86,
    "Question": "What is an antiparticle?",
    "Answer": "particles with the same mass but opposite charge"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 87,
    "Question": "State the name of the anti electron",
    "Answer": "Positron"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 88,
    "Question": "Define a hadron",
    "Answer": "Hadrons are any particle made up of quarks. Hadrons are not fundamental. Hadrons can be either Baryons or mesons."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 89,
    "Question": "What force are hadrons subject to?",
    "Answer": "Strong nuclear force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 90,
    "Question": "Define a baryon",
    "Answer": "Baryons are made up of three quarks and have a baryon number of 1."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 91,
    "Question": "State some common baryons",
    "Answer": "Protons and neutrons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 92,
    "Question": "Which is the most stable baryon?",
    "Answer": "Proton"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 93,
    "Question": "Define a meson",
    "Answer": "Mesons are classified as hadrons as they are made of quarks. Mesons contain a quark and an antiquark have a baryon number of 0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 94,
    "Question": "Name some typical mesons",
    "Answer": "Pions and Kaons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 95,
    "Question": "A particle made up of 3 quarks is called?",
    "Answer": "A baryon"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 96,
    "Question": "A particle is that is made up of a quark and anti quark is called?",
    "Answer": "Meson"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 97,
    "Question": "Name some leptons",
    "Answer": "Electrons, neutrinos, Tau, muon"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 98,
    "Question": "State the mass and charge of a neutrino",
    "Answer": "mass = 0 charge = 0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 99,
    "Question": "What force controls leptons?",
    "Answer": "Leptons are subject to the weak nuclear force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 100,
    "Question": "What type of particle is a muon?",
    "Answer": "A lepton"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 101,
    "Question": "In a nuclear event what must be conserved?",
    "Answer": "Charge, Baryon number, Lepton number, Energy, Momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 102,
    "Question": "What force of nature creates strange particles?",
    "Answer": "Strange particles are made through the strong interaction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 103,
    "Question": "What force allows strange particles to decay?",
    "Answer": "Strange particles decay through the weak interaction (e.g. Kaons)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 104,
    "Question": "Why must strange particles be created in pairs?",
    "Answer": "To conserve strangeness"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 105,
    "Question": "When must strangeness be conserved?",
    "Answer": "When strange particles are made in pairs. Strangeness is conserved with the strong interaction (only the weak interaction can change the type of quark, so there must be the same number of strange particles before and after)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 106,
    "Question": "When can strangeness change?",
    "Answer": "Strangeness can change by +1, 0 or -1 in the weak interaction when a strange particles decay"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 107,
    "Question": "Define annihilation",
    "Answer": "If a particle and anti-particle meet they will annihilate each other and their entire mass is converted into energy into the form of two identical gamma photons (e.g. PET scanners)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 108,
    "Question": "Why are 2 identical gamma photons produced in annihilation?",
    "Answer": "To conserve energy and momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 109,
    "Question": "How many gamma photons are produced in annihilation?",
    "Answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 110,
    "Question": "During annihilation what is the energy of one of the gamma photons?",
    "Answer": "The rest mass of one of the original particles. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 111,
    "Question": "When a particle and antiparticle meet and the mass is converted to energy, this is called?",
    "Answer": "Annihilation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 112,
    "Question": "Define pair production",
    "Answer": "In pair production a single photon vanishes and its energy is converted into mass in the form of a particle and its anti-particle. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 113,
    "Question": "What is the condition required for pair production?",
    "Answer": "This can only happen if the energy of the photon is enough to produce the (rest) mass of the particle and anti particle."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 114,
    "Question": "In pair production what happens if the initial photon has more energy than needed to produce the rest mass of both particles?",
    "Answer": "The particle and anti particle take the extra energy away as kinetic energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 115,
    "Question": "What is the minimum energy for pair production?",
    "Answer": "Rest energy of particle + rest energy of antiparticle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 116,
    "Question": "What group of particles are a type of hadron made of 3 quarks?",
    "Answer": "Hadrons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 117,
    "Question": "What is quark confinement?",
    "Answer": "The energy required to produce a separation of two quarks far exceeds the pair production energy of a quark-antiquark pair, so instead of pulling out an isolated quark, you produce mesons as the produced quark-antiquark pairs combine."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 118,
    "Question": "Define an exchange particle",
    "Answer": "Exchange particles are how forces act between two particles. They are virtual particles and only exist for a very short amount of time. They can transfer energy, charge force and momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 119,
    "Question": "For the strong nuclear force state: the particles affected, the exchange particle and the range",
    "Answer": "Nucleons (all hadrons)Gluons and Pions. Range up to 3 fm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 120,
    "Question": "For the electromagnetic force state: the particles affected, the exchange particle and the range",
    "Answer": "Charged particles, Virtual photons, infinite range"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 121,
    "Question": "For the weak nuclear force state: the particles affected, the exchange particle",
    "Answer": "Responsible for beta decay and changing quarks e.g. u to d. W+, W- bosons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 122,
    "Question": "For the gravitational force state: the particles affected, the exchange particle and the range",
    "Answer": "all particles with mass, Graviton, Infinite"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 123,
    "Question": "What is electron capture?",
    "Answer": "Electron capture is a process in which the proton-rich nucleus absorbs an electron. This process changes a nuclear proton to a neutron and simultaneously causes the emission of an electron neutrino"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 124,
    "Question": "What is an electron-proton collision?",
    "Answer": "An electron collides at high speed with a proton. The proton decays into a neutron and an electron neutrino."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 125,
    "Question": "What are the similarities and differences between electron capture and electron proton collision",
    "Answer": "Similarities - both change a nuclear proton to a neutron and simultaneously causes the emission of an electron neutrino. Differences - In electron-proton collision the electron is the particle that's acting because its being fired at a proton so the W boson comes from the electron. It must be the W- to conserve charge. With electron capture the exchange particle is the W+(moving to the right)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 126,
    "Question": "Under certain conditions a photon may be converted into two particles, what is this called?",
    "Answer": "Pair production"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 127,
    "Question": "What type of mesons are strange?",
    "Answer": "Kaons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 128,
    "Question": "What type of mesons are not strange?",
    "Answer": "Pions"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 129,
    "Question": "State the quark structure of an antibaryon",
    "Answer": "3 antiquarks"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 130,
    "Question": "Give one property of an antiparticle that is the same for the normal particle",
    "Answer": "Rest energy or Rest mass"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 131,
    "Question": "Give one property of an antiparticle that is different to the normal particle.",
    "Answer": "One of: charge, quark composition, baryon number, lepton number, strangeness"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 132,
    "Question": "What is the baryon number of a Kaon or a Pion",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 133,
    "Question": "What fundamental forces can an electron experience?",
    "Answer": "Weak, electromagnetic, gravitational (although negligible)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 134,
    "Question": "What fundamental forces can a proton experience?",
    "Answer": "Weak, strong, electromagnetic, gravitational (negligible)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 135,
    "Question": "What fundamental forces can a neutron experience?",
    "Answer": "Weak, strong, gravitational (negligible)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 136,
    "Question": "What force of nature is present when there is a virtual photon?",
    "Answer": "Electromagnetism"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 137,
    "Question": "What force of nature is present when there is a gluon or pion?",
    "Answer": "Strong"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 138,
    "Question": "What force of nature is present when there is a graviton?",
    "Answer": "Gravity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Particles",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 3,
    "No.": 139,
    "Question": "What force of nature is present when there is a boson?",
    "Answer": "Weak interaction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 140,
    "Question": "Define a photon",
    "Answer": "a packet (quanta) of energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 141,
    "Question": "State the order of the electromagnetic spectrum, in terms of increasing frequency",
    "Answer": "Radio waves, Microwaves, Infrared, Visible, Ultraviolet, X-rays, Gamma rays"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 142,
    "Question": "What do all electromagnetic waves have in common?",
    "Answer": "They all travel at the speed of light in a vacuum. They are transverse waves."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 143,
    "Question": "How are electromagnetic waves emitted?",
    "Answer": "From a charged particle when it loses energy, this can happen when: An electron moves from a higher to a lower energy state or A fast moving electron is stopped e.g. x-rays"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 144,
    "Question": "Which regions of the EM spectrum have photon energies greater than visible light?",
    "Answer": "UV, X-Ray, Gamma"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 145,
    "Question": "Which regions of the EM spectrum have photon energies less than visible light?",
    "Answer": "IR, Microwave, Radio wave"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 146,
    "Question": "Which EM wave as the shortest wavelength/highest frequency?",
    "Answer": "Gamma"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 147,
    "Question": "Which EM wave as the longest wavelength/lowest frequency?",
    "Answer": "Radio"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 148,
    "Question": "What are the wavelengths of the visible spectrum?",
    "Answer": "400-700nm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 149,
    "Question": "What is a typical order of magnitude wavelength of a gamma radiation?",
    "Answer": "10^-12 m"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 150,
    "Question": "What is a typical order of magnitude wavelength of a microwave?",
    "Answer": "10^-2 m"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 151,
    "Question": "What is a typical order of magnitude wavelength of a radio waves?",
    "Answer": "10^2 m"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 152,
    "Question": "What is the relationship between photon energy and frequency?",
    "Answer": "Directly proportional"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 153,
    "Question": "What is the relationship between photon energy and wavelength?",
    "Answer": "inversely proportional"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 154,
    "Question": "Define an eV",
    "Answer": "1 eV is the energy gained by an electron passing through a potential difference of 1 V"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 155,
    "Question": "Describe the photoelectric effect experiment?",
    "Answer": "An insulating rod is given a negative charge. The negative charge is passed onto a zinc plate. The charge moves down onto the gold leaf, The gold leaf repels and deflects away from the centre, Various light source are shone onto the zinc plate"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 156,
    "Question": "Describe the observations of the photoelectric experiment when visible light is used",
    "Answer": "If a filament lamp (lower frequency) is used the electroscope doesn't discharge (gold leaf doesn't move)When very intense visible light is used, no electrons are emitted"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 157,
    "Question": "Describe the observations of the photoelectric experiment when UV is used",
    "Answer": "When UV light (high frequency) light is shown on the zinc plate the leaf falls immediately so electrons are being lost from the plate. If very low intensity UV light is used the discharge starts immediately"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 158,
    "Question": "Describe the interaction in the photoelectric effect",
    "Answer": "A single photon is absorbed by a single surface electron in a one to one interaction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 159,
    "Question": "Which has a higher frequency visible light or UV",
    "Answer": "UV"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 160,
    "Question": "Explain why the kinetic energy of the photoelectrons emitted has a range of values up to a certain maximum.",
    "Answer": "Electron close to the surface escape with the most Kinetic energy. Electrons deeper in the metal need to use energy to move to the surface before escaping"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 161,
    "Question": "What are the three main observations in the photoelectric effect that shows light can not be interactive as a wave?",
    "Answer": "A threshold frequency, photoelectrons having a maximum kinetic energy and photoelectrons emitted immediately"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 162,
    "Question": "Why does a threshold frequency show light is not interacting as a wave?",
    "Answer": "If light was interacting as a wave electrons should be emitted at all frequencies"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 163,
    "Question": "Why does the photoelectrons having a maximum kinetic energy show that light is not interactive as a wave?",
    "Answer": "Waves could transfer any amount of energy so there would be no limit on kinetic energy. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 164,
    "Question": "Why does photoelectrons leaving immediately prove light cant be acting as a wave?",
    "Answer": "If light was acting like a wave energy could build up over a period of time and electrons could be released with a delay"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 165,
    "Question": "Which has higher photon energy red of blue visible light?",
    "Answer": "Blue - higher frequency"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 166,
    "Question": "Define threshold frequency",
    "Answer": "Threshold frequency minimum frequency of radiation needed to release photoelectrons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 167,
    "Question": "The minimum frequency of radiation needed to release photoelectrons is called?",
    "Answer": "Threshold frequency"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 168,
    "Question": "Define work function",
    "Answer": "Work function energy an electron must gain to be released from the metal"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 169,
    "Question": "The energy an electron must gain to be released from the metal is called?",
    "Answer": "Work function"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 170,
    "Question": "Define intensity",
    "Answer": "The amount of energy arriving per second per m^2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 171,
    "Question": "The amount of energy arriving per second per m^2 is known as?",
    "Answer": "Intensity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 172,
    "Question": "What is the photoelectric effect?",
    "Answer": "When light of a high enough frequency falls on a metal surface and causes electrons to be emitted from the surface"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 173,
    "Question": "In the photoelectric effect what is the affect of increasing intensity of visible light?",
    "Answer": "No effect, the frequency will be below the threshold frequency so no electrons will be released"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 174,
    "Question": "In the photoelectric effect , if UV radiation is used with a constant frequency, what is the effect of increasing the intensity?",
    "Answer": "More photoelectrons are released each second - If intensity is increasing but each photon has a constant energy (E = hf) then more photons must be arriving and interacting with electrons per second. Each photoelectron will have a constant kinetic energy as the energy of the incoming photons is constant (E=hf)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 175,
    "Question": "In the photoelectric effect, if UV radiation of constant intensity is used. What is the effect of increasing the frequency?",
    "Answer": "Less electrons would be released each second - the same energy must be arriving per second but each photon has more energy - so less photons must be arriving per second Each released photoelectron will have more kinetic energy as the incoming photons have more energy (E = hf)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 176,
    "Question": "What name is given to the voltage that can be applied to a photocell to stop photoelectrons?",
    "Answer": "Stopping potential"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 177,
    "Question": "Describe the stopping potential experiment",
    "Answer": "Photoelectrons are emitted from a metal surface. They then have to travel towards the negative terminal of a battery. This means they have to do work against the potential difference. The stopping potential is the p.d. needed to stop the fastest electrons with the maximum kinetic energy. The work done by the p.d. is equal to the initial energy of the electrons. W = VQ"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 178,
    "Question": "From a graph of kinetic energy against frequency what can be found?",
    "Answer": "Gradient = h. x intercept = threshold frequency. y intercept = - work function"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 179,
    "Question": "Describe excitation",
    "Answer": "An electron can move up an energy level by gaining energy (e.g. via heating or collisions with other particles or absorbing photons). This is called excitation."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 180,
    "Question": "Describe how excitation happens via collision with electrons",
    "Answer": "Electrons collide with atoms transferring some, none or all of its energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 181,
    "Question": "Describe excitation via electron collision when the electron has the same energy of the difference between energy levels?",
    "Answer": "If the electron has the same energy as the difference between energy levels then it will transfer all of its energy and the electron will stop."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 182,
    "Question": "Describe excitation via electron collision when the electron has more energy then the difference between energy levels",
    "Answer": "If the electron has more energy than the difference between the energy levels, then excitation will occur and the electron will take the excess energy away as kinetic energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 183,
    "Question": "Describe excitation via electron collision when he electron has less energy than the difference between energy levels",
    "Answer": "If the electron has less energy than the difference between the energy levels then it will be deflected by the atom with no loss in kinetic energy or excitation."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 184,
    "Question": "Describe excitation by using photons",
    "Answer": "Electrons in an atom absorb a photon and all of its energy. This can only happen if the energy of the photon is exactly equal to the energy the electron would need to gain to move to a higher energy level. If the photons energy is smaller of larger than the difference between the two energy levels then it wont be absorbed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 185,
    "Question": "Describe relaxation",
    "Answer": "An electron can move down to a lower energy level by losing energy. This is done by releasing a photon. This is called relaxation."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 186,
    "Question": "Define ionisation",
    "Answer": "If an electron gains enough energy it can escape the atom. This is called ionisation."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 187,
    "Question": "How much energy is assigned to an electron that has just been ionised?",
    "Answer": "O J"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 188,
    "Question": "Why do energy levels have negative values?",
    "Answer": "For an electron that is bound to the atom, energy has to be added to release it. Work has to be done to move an electron to a higher energy level. But we define an electron as just being ionized as having zero energy. So we say that the electron in an energy level has negative energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 189,
    "Question": "Explain how fluorescent tubes work",
    "Answer": "Fluorescent tubes contain mercury vapour across which a high p.d. is applied. The high voltage accelerates free electrons. The free electrons collide with the mercury atoms and excites them to a higher energy level. When these electrons relax they lose high energy photons in the UV range. A phosphorous coating on the inside of the tube absorbs these photons, which excites the electrons to a higher energy level. These electrons then relax and release lower energy photons of visible light."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 190,
    "Question": "What substance fills a fluorescent tube and what type of photons does it release?",
    "Answer": "Mercury - it emits UV photons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 191,
    "Question": "What substance coats a fluorescent tube and what type of photons does it release?",
    "Answer": "Phosphorous and it emits visible light photons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 192,
    "Question": "What is a line emission spectrum?",
    "Answer": "Given out by gas atoms which have been excited through discharge of electricity or by heating to high temps."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 193,
    "Question": "Explain why line spectra are seen as discrete lines",
    "Answer": "Line spectra are seen as discrete lines as they contains only specific energies, frequencies and wavelengths. The electrons in the atom can only orbit at certain distances (shells/levels) from the nucleus, i.e. the radius of the orbit is â€œquantizedâ€An excited electrons will jump down (relax) to a lower energy level. In jumping down the electrons emit a photon of energy equal to the difference in the energy between the two levels. (E= hf)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 194,
    "Question": "What is a continuous spectrum?",
    "Answer": "A continuous spectrum is a spectrum in which all wavelengths/frequencies are present between certain limits."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 195,
    "Question": "How is a continuous spectrum produced?",
    "Answer": "It is given out by hot glowing objects. All wavelengths are present because the electrons are not bound to atoms and are free so they are not confined to specific energy levels."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 196,
    "Question": "What is an absorption spectrum?",
    "Answer": "A continuous spectra with dark bands"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 197,
    "Question": "How is an absorption spectrum created?",
    "Answer": "Atoms of hot gas absorbing particular frequencies or wavelength as white light passes through."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 198,
    "Question": "State some wave properties",
    "Answer": "Refraction, Diffraction, Interference, Polarisation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 199,
    "Question": "State some particle properties",
    "Answer": "Travels in straight lines, Photoelectric effect, Carrying a charge/mass, Deflection by an electric or magnetic field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 200,
    "Question": "Describe an experiment that showed electrons to behave like waves?",
    "Answer": "Electron diffraction through graphite - Electrons fired  pass through a graphite target. A series of bright rings can be seen on a phosphorescent screen."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 201,
    "Question": "State the evidence that electrons can act like waves",
    "Answer": "Electrons are being diffracted as they pass through the graphite. Electrons are constructively interfering to produce bright rings. Electrons are destructively interfering to produce dark rings. The same pattern build up with just one electron at a time."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 202,
    "Question": "What is the condition required for noticeable diffraction?",
    "Answer": "The wavelength must be similar to the size of the gap it is passing through"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 203,
    "Question": "Describe the two main methods that cause electrons to be ionised?",
    "Answer": "Collision with electrons and Absorbing a photon"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 204,
    "Question": "How does excitation by collision differ from excitation by a photon?",
    "Answer": "In collision the incoming electron can transfer a proportion of its kinetic energy, in absorption the incoming photon has to give up all of its energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 205,
    "Question": "Which theory of light cannot be used to explain the photoelectric effect?",
    "Answer": "Wave theory"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 206,
    "Question": "What name is given to the ability of something to exhibit wave and particle properties?",
    "Answer": "Wave-particle duality"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 207,
    "Question": "Give one piece of evidence for electrons exhibiting wave behaviour?",
    "Answer": "Electron diffraction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Particles and Radiation",
    "Sub-topic": "Electromagnetic radiation and quantum phenomena ",
    "Specification Reference": "3.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 5,
    "No.": 208,
    "Question": "Give one piece of evidence for light exhibiting particle behaviour?",
    "Answer": "Photoelectric effect"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 209,
    "Question": "Define longitudinal wave",
    "Answer": "A wave with a direction of vibration that is parallel to the direction of energy transfer "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 210,
    "Question": "Define transverse wave",
    "Answer": "A wave with a direction of vibration that is perpendicular to the direction of energy transfer. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 211,
    "Question": "Give an example of a longitudinal wave",
    "Answer": "Sound waves, seismic P waves"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 212,
    "Question": "Give an example of a transverse wave",
    "Answer": "Water waves, EM waves, Seismic S waves"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 213,
    "Question": "Define amplitude of a wave",
    "Answer": "The maximum displacement of the wave from the equilibrium position"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 214,
    "Question": "Give three examples of waves that are transverse",
    "Answer": "Electromagnetic radiation e.g. microwaves, infrared etc, Surface of water, Rope, s waves"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 215,
    "Question": "Give three examples of longitudinal waves",
    "Answer": "Sound, Ultrasound, P waves"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 216,
    "Question": "State the order of the electromagnetic spectrum from lowest frequency/energy to highest frequency/energy",
    "Answer": "Radio, Microwaves, Infrared, Visible, Ultra violet, X - rays, Gamma rays"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 217,
    "Question": "How do we know waves transfer energy?",
    "Answer": "Electromagnetic waves heats things up when they are absorbed, X-rays and gamma rays knock electrons out of their orbits (ionisation)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 218,
    "Question": "Define wavelength",
    "Answer": "The distance from a point on the wave to the same point on the adjacent wave. It is measured in meters"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 219,
    "Question": "Define frequency",
    "Answer": "Is the number of waves that pass a point every second. It is measured in hertz (Hz)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 220,
    "Question": "Define period",
    "Answer": "It is the time taken for each one whole wave to pass a fixed point. It is measured in seconds (s)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 221,
    "Question": "Define phase difference",
    "Answer": "the amount by which one wave lags behind another wave."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 222,
    "Question": "If point B is half a wavelength ahead of point A what is their phase difference?",
    "Answer": "π radians or 180° or in antiphase"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 223,
    "Question": "What units can phase difference be measured in?",
    "Answer": "Phase and phase difference can be measured in: degrees, radians, fractions of a cycle."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 224,
    "Question": "Define monochromatic",
    "Answer": "Single wavelength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 225,
    "Question": "Define coherent",
    "Answer": "Waves with the same frequency, a constant phase difference and a similar amplitude"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 226,
    "Question": "Describe an experiment to measure the speed of sound",
    "Answer": "Start with signal generator + 2 microphones in phase. Move 1 microphone and measure the distance between them. Measure the time delay using the picoscope. collect a range of distance and time measurements. Draw a graph of distance against time. Use the gradient to find the speed of sound."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 227,
    "Question": "Define polarisation",
    "Answer": "Restriction of a wave to a single plane"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 228,
    "Question": "If there are two polarising filters in-between an observer and light, if one is turned about 360 degrees, what would the observer see?",
    "Answer": "Variation in intensity between max and min Two maxima and two minimum in 360 degree rotation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 229,
    "Question": "What waves can be polarised?",
    "Answer": "Transverse "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 230,
    "Question": "State one application of a polarising filter and a reason for its use",
    "Answer": "Camera/sunglasses  - Reduce glare, LCD screens - less power is required, 3D glasses - Enhanced viewing experience"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 231,
    "Question": "Light was originally thought to be a longitudinal wave, why do we now know it is transverse?",
    "Answer": "It was discovered light was polarised by reflection so must be transverse."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 232,
    "Question": "Explain why it is important to correctly align the aerial of a TV to receive the strongest signal",
    "Answer": "Transmitted radio waves are often polarised. Aerial rods must be aligned in the same plane of the wave"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 233,
    "Question": "Define interference",
    "Answer": "Interference is When two waves arrive at the same point and at the same time, the resultant displacement is given by the algebraic sum of the two individual displacements. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 234,
    "Question": "Define constructive interference",
    "Answer": "If two waves meet exactly in phase the amplitudes add up to produce large crests and troughs"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 235,
    "Question": "Define destructive interference",
    "Answer": "If two waves meet exactly out of phase the amplitudes cancel to produce no crests and troughs"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 236,
    "Question": "State the difference between a progressive wave and a standing wave.",
    "Answer": "Progressive (travelling wave) transfer energy from one region to another e.g. light and sound. Standing (stationary waves) Are fixed in space and do not travel. They are caused by the superposition of two identical waves. e.g. waves on a guitar string"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 237,
    "Question": "How are stationary waves formed?",
    "Answer": "Vibrations cause waves travels along the string towards the pulley. The waves reflect from the pulley and travel back to the vibration generator. The two waves meet and constructively and destructively interfere."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 238,
    "Question": "What are the conditions required for standing waves to be formed?",
    "Answer": "The waves must have the same frequency and amplitude."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 239,
    "Question": "Define a node",
    "Answer": "NO Displacement -  Positive displacement from one wave is cancelled by an equal negative displacement from the other wave. (Destructive interference)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 240,
    "Question": "Define an antinode",
    "Answer": "A point of maximum displacement (constructive interference)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 241,
    "Question": "For a string that is fixed at both ends what are the rules for nodes and antinodes?",
    "Answer": "There must be a node at each end."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 242,
    "Question": "How can a guitarist raise the fundamental frequency of vibration in their string? ",
    "Answer": "Tighten the string, shorter length of string, Use a string of lower mass per unit length"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 243,
    "Question": "For a closed pipe what are the rules for nodes and antinodes",
    "Answer": "The closed end of the pipe is always a node, the open end of the pipe is always an antinode"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 244,
    "Question": "For an open pipe what are the rules for nodes and antinodes",
    "Answer": "There must be an antinode at each end"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 245,
    "Question": "What is the distance between 2 successive nodes in a stationary wave?",
    "Answer": "Half a wavelength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 246,
    "Question": "What is the distance between a node and adjacent antinode in a stationary wave?",
    "Answer": "Quarter of a wavelength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 247,
    "Question": "What is the distance between 2 successive antinodes in a stationary wave?",
    "Answer": "Half a wavelength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 248,
    "Question": "2 points on a stationary wave are separated by 2 nodes. What is their phase difference?",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 249,
    "Question": "2 points on a stationary wave are separated by a node. What is their phase difference?",
    "Answer": "180˚ or π radians"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 250,
    "Question": "Define intensity",
    "Answer": "Energy arriving per second per unit area or power per unit area"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 251,
    "Question": "Define diffraction",
    "Answer": "The spreading of waves on passing through a gap or near an edge"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 252,
    "Question": "When is diffraction noticeable?",
    "Answer": "When the wavelength is similar in size to the gap/obstacle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 253,
    "Question": "Describe the intensity pattern for single slit diffraction for red light",
    "Answer": "A bright red central maximum (where the majority of the energy arrives)Alternating dark and bright fringes either side of the central maximum. The central maximum is twice the width of the outer bright fringes, The outer bring fringes have much less intensity than the central maximum. Peak intensity of each fringe decreases with distance from the centre."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 254,
    "Question": "Describe the diffraction pattern of white light through a single slit?",
    "Answer": "A central bright maximum that is white. Alternating dark and bright fringes either side of the central maximum. The outer bright fringes are the spectra of colours from Violet to red. (violet has a shorter wavelength), This is because white light is a mixture of colours each with a different wavelength."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 255,
    "Question": "State two ways a diffraction pattern on single slit would change if the slit became narrower",
    "Answer": "Increased diffraction - main peak would be more spread out and Lower intensity - less light could get through the smaller slit"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 256,
    "Question": "Using the single slit equation state 2 ways to increase the angle of diffraction",
    "Answer": "Larger wavelength and Smaller gap size"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 257,
    "Question": "For single slit diffraction how does increasing the slit width affect the central maximum?",
    "Answer": "Increasing the slit width will decrease the amount of diffraction so the central maximum is narrower. As the slit is wider more light can pass through so the intensity of the central maximum will increase."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 258,
    "Question": "For single slit diffraction how does increasing the wavelength affect the central maximum?",
    "Answer": "Increasing the wavelength increases the amount of diffraction. This means the central maximum is wider and the intensity will be lower. The outer fringes will also become further apart"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 259,
    "Question": "What is significant about the central bright fringe in a single slit diffraction pattern?",
    "Answer": "It is twice the width of subsequent fringes,"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 260,
    "Question": "Explain how Young's double slit arrangement produces interference fringes",
    "Answer": "Light diffracted at both slits and overlap and interfere. Where path lengths differ by whole number of wavelengths, constructive interference occurs producing a bright fringe. Where path lengths differ by 0.5 x n wavelengths, destructive interference occurs producing a dark fringe."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 261,
    "Question": "Explain how to set up Youngs double slit experiment to ensure the waves passing through both slits are coherent",
    "Answer": "After the light source have a single slit, followed by the double slits The first narrow single slit gives wide diffraction to ensure that both second slits are illuminated equally Path difference to second slits are of constant length giving constant phase difference "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 262,
    "Question": "In the double slit experiment what happens to fringe spacing is slit-screen distance is doubled and slit spacing is halved?",
    "Answer": "Fringe spacing increases by factor of 4"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 263,
    "Question": "In Youngs double slit what causes the bright and dark fringes?",
    "Answer": "Bright fringes - waves arriving in phase - constructive interference. Dark fringes - waves arriving out of phase - destructive interference"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 264,
    "Question": "Describe the intensity pattern produced by Young's double slit experiment.",
    "Answer": "A series of bright and dark fringes. The bright fringes have equal intensity and are evenly spaced."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 265,
    "Question": "Describe the intensity pattern seen when using white light in Youngs double slit experiment",
    "Answer": "Central fringe would be white. Dark fringes would be either side of white fringe. Side fringes are spectra of colours"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 266,
    "Question": "Using the double slit equation state 3 ways to increase the width between the slits",
    "Answer": "Larger wavelength,  Increased distance to screen, Decrease the slit separation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 267,
    "Question": "In Youngs double slit experiment what changes would you see if you replaced a blue light source with a red light source.",
    "Answer": "Red has a larger wavelength than blue so: Central fringe would be wider, Fringe spacing would be larger"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 268,
    "Question": "In Young's double slit how can the fringe spacing be measured accurately?",
    "Answer": "Measure across several fringes and divide by the number of fringes. Measure from the centre of a dark fringe to the centre of another dark fringe. The centre is easier to find on a dark fringe rather than a bright fringe. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 269,
    "Question": "Use wave theory to explain how the fringe pattern is formed in Youngs double slit experiment",
    "Answer": "Slits act as coherent sources, Waves diffract at slits, Waves superpose, Bright patches: constructive interference, Dark patches: destructive"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 270,
    "Question": "State and explain the effect of using a laser with a shorter wavelength on the maxima spacing in Young's double slit",
    "Answer": "Maxima closer together as fringe spacing decreases. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 271,
    "Question": "State two requirements for two light sources to be coherent",
    "Answer": "Same wavelength or frequency. Constant phase difference"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 272,
    "Question": "What is the role of a diffraction grating?",
    "Answer": "Split light into its separate wavelengths"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 273,
    "Question": "For a diffraction grating state and explain what happens to angle of diffraction¸ when wavelength decreases?",
    "Answer": "Angle gets smaller"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 274,
    "Question": "For a diffraction grating describe the pattern seen with white light?",
    "Answer": "A white central maximum, Following fringes will be the spectra of colours, from violet to red as violet has a shorter wavelength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 275,
    "Question": "Describe the pattern seen with red light passing through a diffraction grating",
    "Answer": "Red light is monochromatic so, red central maximum. Outer orders of diffraction are also red"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 276,
    "Question": "When using red light of wavelength 650nm and a diffraction grating with 500 lines per m what is the highest order maximum observable?",
    "Answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Progressive and stationary waves",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.1",
    "Teaching Order": 7,
    "No.": 277,
    "Question": "In a diffraction grating how can the maximum number of orders to calculated?",
    "Answer": "Put the angle equal to 90 and then round down to the nearest whole number."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 278,
    "Question": "What is the name given to the change in direction of a light ray due to a change in speed?",
    "Answer": "Refraction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 279,
    "Question": "Why does light change direction when it enters a glass block?",
    "Answer": "Slows down as glass has a higher refractive index than air"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 280,
    "Question": "What is the definition of refractive index?",
    "Answer": "n = speed of light in a vacuum / speed of light in the medium"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 281,
    "Question": " when monochromatic light passes from glass into air what is the effect on speed, wavelength and frequency? ",
    "Answer": "Speed increases, wavelength increases, frequency stays constant "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 282,
    "Question": " when monochromatic light passes from air into glass what is the effect on speed, wavelength and frequency? ",
    "Answer": "Speed decreases, wavelength decreases, frequency stays constant "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 283,
    "Question": "What is the name for the part of an optical fibre that is around the core?",
    "Answer": "Cladding"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 284,
    "Question": "What are the two conditions required for TIR?",
    "Answer": "TIR only occurs when ray travels from higher refractive index to lower refractive and as long as the incident angle is greater than the critical angle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 285,
    "Question": "What happens if angle of incidence is larger than critical angle?",
    "Answer": "Total Internal Reflection"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 286,
    "Question": "What happens if angle of incidence is equal to critical angle?",
    "Answer": "Travel along boundary (90˚ refraction)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 287,
    "Question": "What happens if angle of incidence is smaller than critical angle?",
    "Answer": "Refraction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 288,
    "Question": "In fibre optics cables why is absorption a problem?",
    "Answer": "Absorption is where some of the signa's energy is absorbed by the material of the fibre. This energy loss results in the amplitude of the signal being reduced. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 289,
    "Question": "In fibre optics cables why is dispersion a problem?",
    "Answer": "Dispersion causes pulse broadening. The received pulse is broader than the initial signal. Broadened pulses can overlap each other leading to information loss."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 290,
    "Question": "State and explain an advantage of a smaller diameter core",
    "Answer": "Reduce multipath dispersion, which would cause poor resolution"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 291,
    "Question": "Describe the structure of a step-index optical fibre outlining the purpose of the core and cladding",
    "Answer": "Core is transmission medium for electromagnetic waves to progress by total internal reflection. Cladding has a lower refractive index to allow total internal reflection to occur. Cladding offers protection from scratching that could lead to light loss"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 292,
    "Question": "State and explain two physical properties of the light produced by a laser which makes it different to that produced by a lamp",
    "Answer": "Monochromatic - Waves of single wavelength. Coherent Waves produced in constant phase."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 293,
    "Question": "What is modal dispersion?",
    "Answer": "Is caused by light rays entering the cable at different angles. This causes them to take different paths and therefore take different amounts of time to travel."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 294,
    "Question": "How can modal dispersion be reduced?",
    "Answer": "To reduce modal dispersion by using a single mode fibre in which light is only allowed to follow a very narrow path."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 295,
    "Question": "What is material dispersion",
    "Answer": "Is caused by different amounts of refraction experienced by different wavelengths of light. This will cause some wavelengths to be slowed down more and take longer to travel down the cable."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 296,
    "Question": "Discuss two changes to reduce material pulse broadening of white light",
    "Answer": "Monochromatic source so speed is constant. Shorter repeaters so pulse is reformed before significant broadening occurs"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 297,
    "Question": "Blue light has a higher refractive index fibre than red light, explain how this difference results in a change in a pulse of white light by the time it leaves the fibre",
    "Answer": "Blue travels slower than red due to greater refractive index. Red reaches the end of the fibre before blue leading to material pulse broadening"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 298,
    "Question": "When light goes from a lower to a higher optical density (e.g. air to glass) what is the affect on speed, wavelength, frequency and direction?",
    "Answer": "Speed decreases, Frequency stays the same, Wavelength decrease, It bends towards the normal"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 299,
    "Question": "When light goes from a higher to a lower optical density (e.g. glass to air) what is the affect on speed, wavelength, frequency and direction?",
    "Answer": "Speed increases, Frequency stays the same, Wavelength increases, It bends away from the normal"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 300,
    "Question": "Explain why optical fibres used for communication need to have cladding",
    "Answer": "Keeps signal secure. Keeps most light rays in"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 301,
    "Question": "Why are optical fibre cables made as thin as possible?",
    "Answer": "To reduce multipath/multimode dispersion. This would cause light of different angles arriving at different times causing pulse broadening. Reduces data loss Less light is lost so better quality signal. Increased probability of TIR as incident angle less likely to be below the critical angle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 302,
    "Question": "State some applications of optical fibres",
    "Answer": "Endoscope - improve medical diagnosis/reduce infection Fibre optics - improve rate of transmission of data"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Waves",
    "Sub-topic": "Refraction, diffraction and interference",
    "Specification Reference": "3.3.2",
    "Teaching Order": 9,
    "No.": 303,
    "Question": "Explain how glass cladding around the optical fibre's core improves the security of data being transmitted through it and give a reason ",
    "Answer": "Light doesn't enter cladding so can't pass across from one fibre to a neighbouring fibre. Fibres without cladding can allow light to pass between fibres when scratched or linked by moisture. Personal data must be transmitted along fibres where there is no danger of light leakage. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 304,
    "Question": "Acceleration, momentum and weight are examples of what type of quantity?",
    "Answer": "Vector"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 305,
    "Question": "What is a vector quantity?",
    "Answer": "A quantity with both magnitude and direction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 306,
    "Question": "What is a scalar quantity?",
    "Answer": "A quantity with only a magnitude associated with it"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 307,
    "Question": "What is the sum of two or more vectors called?",
    "Answer": "Resultant"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 308,
    "Question": "Give three examples of scalar quantities",
    "Answer": "Any three from speed, distance, pressure, temperature, mass, density, power"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 309,
    "Question": "Give three examples of vector quantities",
    "Answer": "Acceleration, velocity, displacement, Force, Weight, momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 310,
    "Question": "State the  forces that will act on a helicopter that is moving horizontally",
    "Answer": "Lift, Air resistance, Weight, Thrust"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 311,
    "Question": "How can drawn force vectors be arranged to show that an object has constant velocity?",
    "Answer": "Closed triangle of vectors. This shows the forces are in equilibrium."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 312,
    "Question": "What is the difference between a vector quantity and a scalar quantity?",
    "Answer": "Vector has a direction, scalar does not."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 313,
    "Question": "A value with magnitude only is a ________?",
    "Answer": "Scalar"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 314,
    "Question": "A value with magnitude and direction is a ____________?",
    "Answer": "Vector"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 315,
    "Question": "Distance and speed are examples of _________ quantities",
    "Answer": "scalar"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 316,
    "Question": "What is the name given to a vector formed by adding vectors together?",
    "Answer": "Resultant vector"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 317,
    "Question": "Force, displacement and velocity are examples of __________ quantities",
    "Answer": "Vector"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 318,
    "Question": "What is a moment?",
    "Answer": "A moment is the turning effect of a force around a turning point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 319,
    "Question": "How do you calculate a moment?",
    "Answer": "moment = F x d"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 320,
    "Question": "What name is given to a pair of forces of equal size which act perpendicular to each other in opposite directions?",
    "Answer": "A couple"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 321,
    "Question": "How can you calculate the centre of mass of an irregularly shaped object?",
    "Answer": "Hang it from a point, draw a line down, do this 3 times, the point where the three lines meet will be the COM."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 322,
    "Question": "How can you use the principle of moments to calculate the mass of a beam?",
    "Answer": "Hang the beam from a point (not it's COM) and hang masses from the beam, taking moments around one side will allow you to calculate the moments around the COM."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 323,
    "Question": "What is the name of the single point at which an object's mass appears to act?",
    "Answer": "centre of mass"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 324,
    "Question": "The centre of mass of an object is defined as?",
    "Answer": "the single point at which the objects weight appears to act."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 325,
    "Question": "What unit are moments measured in?",
    "Answer": "N m"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 326,
    "Question": "Define the moment of a force",
    "Answer": "Product of the force and the perpendicular distance between the line of action of the force and the turning point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 327,
    "Question": "State the principle of moments",
    "Answer": "The principle of moments states that for a system in equilibrium, the sum of the clockwise moments about a point is equal to the sum of the anticlockwise moments about the same point."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 328,
    "Question": "For a uniform regular solid, where will its centre of mass be?",
    "Answer": "The centre of the object"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 329,
    "Question": "Define a couple",
    "Answer": "A couple is a pair of forces of equal size which act parallel to each other, but in opposite directions."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 330,
    "Question": "What affect will a couple have on an object?",
    "Answer": "It will cause the object to rotate"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 331,
    "Question": "Explain why a wine glass containing wine is less stable than an empty one.",
    "Answer": "The centre of mass is lower on an empty wine glass, so will be more stable, than a full one."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 332,
    "Question": "How can an object be made more stable?",
    "Answer": "Widen the base of the object or lower the centre of mass"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 333,
    "Question": "If the centre of mass of a beam is directly over a pivot, how will the beam move?",
    "Answer": "The beam will remain stationary as there is no resultant moment."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 334,
    "Question": "In order to calculate which direction a see saw will rotate in, what do you need to calculate?",
    "Answer": "The clockwise and anticlockwise moments around the pivot."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Vectors, Scalars and Moments",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 335,
    "Question": "State and explain a feature of a crane that helps prevent it from falling over when lifting heavy things",
    "Answer": "A counterweight provides a sufficiently large moment in the opposite direction. They also have wide heavy bases."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 336,
    "Question": "What is meant by speed?",
    "Answer": "How fast something is moving, regardless of direction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 337,
    "Question": "What is meant by displacement ?",
    "Answer": "How far an object has travelled form its start point in a given direction."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 338,
    "Question": "What is the definition of velocity?",
    "Answer": "The rate of change of displacement (speed in a given direction)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 339,
    "Question": "What is the definition of acceleration?",
    "Answer": "The rate of change of velocity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 340,
    "Question": "In the SUVAT equations, what does s represent?",
    "Answer": "Displacement (m)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 341,
    "Question": "In the SUVAT equations, what does u represent?",
    "Answer": "Initial velocity (ms-1)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 342,
    "Question": "In the SUVAT equations, what does v represent?",
    "Answer": "Final velocity (ms-1)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 343,
    "Question": "In the SUVAT equations, what does a represent?",
    "Answer": "Acceleration (ms-2)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 344,
    "Question": "In the SUVAT equations, what does represent?",
    "Answer": "Time (s)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 345,
    "Question": "Under what conditions can the SUVAT equations be used?",
    "Answer": "Constant acceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 346,
    "Question": "What does free fall mean?",
    "Answer": "Only force acting is gravity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 347,
    "Question": "If an object is dropped. What is its initial velocity, u?",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 348,
    "Question": "If an object comes to rest. What is its final velocity, v?",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 349,
    "Question": "When a ball is thrown upwards, what is its velocity at its highest point?",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 350,
    "Question": "When a ball is thrown upwards, what is its acceleration on the way down?",
    "Answer": "g = 9.81"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 351,
    "Question": "When a ball is thrown upwards, what is its acceleration on the way up?",
    "Answer": "g =9.81"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 352,
    "Question": "What does the gradient of a displacement-time graph tell you?",
    "Answer": "The velocity of the object"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 353,
    "Question": "How would a stationary object be represented on a displacement-time  graph?",
    "Answer": "Straight horizontal line with 0 gradient"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 354,
    "Question": "On a displacement-time  graph a straight, diagonal line represents?",
    "Answer": "constant velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 355,
    "Question": "On a displacement-time  graph a steeper gradient represents?",
    "Answer": "Larger velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 356,
    "Question": "On a displacement-time  graph a shallower gradient represents?",
    "Answer": "Smaller velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 357,
    "Question": "On a displacement-time graph an upward curve represents?",
    "Answer": "acceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 358,
    "Question": "On a displacement-time graph a curved line becoming horizontal represents?",
    "Answer": "deceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 359,
    "Question": "On a displacement-time graph a horizontal line represents",
    "Answer": "A stationary object"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 360,
    "Question": "On a displacement-time  graph the gradient is used to calculate the?",
    "Answer": "Velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 361,
    "Question": "On a curved displacement-time graph showing an accelerating object, how can you calculate instantaneous velocity?",
    "Answer": "Draw a tangent and find the gradient at that point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 362,
    "Question": "On a velocity time graph an upwards, diagonal straight line represents ",
    "Answer": "Constant acceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 363,
    "Question": "On a velocity - time graph a steeper gradient represents?",
    "Answer": "Greater acceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 364,
    "Question": "On a velocity - time graph a shallower gradient represents?",
    "Answer": "Smaller acceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 365,
    "Question": "On a velocity time graph a downwards, diagonal straight line represents ",
    "Answer": "deceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 366,
    "Question": "On a velocity time graph a horizontal line represents ",
    "Answer": "Constant velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 367,
    "Question": "On a velocity time graph a horizontal line along the x-axis represents",
    "Answer": "stationary object"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 368,
    "Question": "On a velocity time graph, when the line falls below the x-axis it indicates that the object is ",
    "Answer": "moving backwards"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 369,
    "Question": "Calculating the gradient of a velocity time graph gives the ",
    "Answer": "acceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 370,
    "Question": "Calculating the area under a velocity time graph gives the ",
    "Answer": "Displacement of the object"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 371,
    "Question": "On a velocity - time graph for a ball being dropped and rebounding. What will the gradient of the line be?",
    "Answer": "g (9.81m s-2)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 372,
    "Question": "On an acceleration - time graph what does a straight line at acceleration = 0 mean?",
    "Answer": "The object is moving at a constant velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 373,
    "Question": "On and acceleration - time graph what does a positive gradient mean?",
    "Answer": "The rate of acceleration is increasing."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 374,
    "Question": "On and acceleration - time graph what does a negative gradient mean?",
    "Answer": "The rate of acceleration is decreasing (above the x-axis).The rate of deceleration is increasing (below the x-axis)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 375,
    "Question": "On and acceleration - time graph what does the area under the graph tell you ?",
    "Answer": "The change in velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 376,
    "Question": "How would you find the velocity from an acceleration - time graph?",
    "Answer": "The area under the graph gives you the velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 377,
    "Question": "What does negative acceleration on an acceleration - time graph show?",
    "Answer": "Deceleration"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 378,
    "Question": "How would constant velocity appear on an acceleration - time graph?",
    "Answer": "Straight, horizontal line along through 0 on the vertical axis."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 379,
    "Question": "True or false? An object with a resultant force of 0 N acting on it must be at rest.",
    "Answer": "False. An object that's moving at a constant velocity will also have 0 resultant force acting on it."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 380,
    "Question": "Three coplanar forces are acting on an object. Describe how you could use a scale drawing to show whether or not the object is in equilibrium.",
    "Answer": "Using a scale drawing. Draw the forces tip to tail. If they form a closed triangle, then the object is in equilibrium."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 381,
    "Question": "True or false? An object suspended from a string will always hang so that its centre of mass is vertically in line with the string.",
    "Answer": "TRUE"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 382,
    "Question": "A student travels into space in a spaceship with a mass of 2.03 x 10^6 kg. When it lands on an unknown planet, the weight of the spaceship is 1.75 x 10^7 N. Determine the gravitational field strength on the unknown planet?",
    "Answer": "8.62 N/kg"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 383,
    "Question": "True of false? An object is in free fall if the only force acting on it is air resistance.",
    "Answer": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 384,
    "Question": "True or false? An object undergoing projectile motion is accelerating in both the horizontal and vertical directions.",
    "Answer": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 385,
    "Question": "An object is travelling at v m/s at an angle, A, above the horizontal. What equation should be used to determine the horizontal component of its velocity?",
    "Answer": "vcosA"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 386,
    "Question": "True or false? The faster an object is moving through air, the lower the air resistance acting on it.",
    "Answer": "False. The faster an object moves through air, the greater the air resistance acting on it."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 387,
    "Question": "What does freefall mean?",
    "Answer": "Freefall is when the only force acting on an object is gravity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 388,
    "Question": "In which direction does g act?",
    "Answer": "Vertically down"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 389,
    "Question": "What's freefall motion called when the object is given an initial velocity?",
    "Answer": "Projectile motion"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 390,
    "Question": "What should you do if you need to use the SUVAT equations on an object that has an initial velocity at an angle to the horizontal?",
    "Answer": "Resolve the velocity into its vertical and horizontal components. Using the vertical velocity for the calculation with the SUVAT equations, to calculate how long it's in the air. Then use the horizontal component of velocity along with the time calculated from the vertical component to calculate the distance the projectile travelled."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 391,
    "Question": "What is the only force present in free fall motion?",
    "Answer": "Weight"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 392,
    "Question": "Describe an experiment you could do to obtain data that you could use to determine the value of g.",
    "Answer": "Using light gates or an electromagnetic timer. Time the time taken for a ball bearing the fall through a certain distance. Take readings for each height and obtain an average."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 393,
    "Question": "Explain how you can plot the data obtained from the measuring g practical on a graph to obtain the value for g.",
    "Answer": "Plotting height against time squared and drawing a line of best fit. Then find the gradient of that line. 1/2 the gradient will give you the acceleration due to gravity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 394,
    "Question": "Ignoring air resistance, which ball will accelerate fastest if dropped. One with a mass of 5kg or one with a mass of 50kg?",
    "Answer": "They will both accelerate at the same rate, g."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 395,
    "Question": "What is the effect of air resistance on the trajectory of a projectile?",
    "Answer": "It will reduced the distance travelled by the projectile. If the projectile starts with vertical velocity, it will reduce the height the projectile reaches."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 396,
    "Question": "What is meant by friction?",
    "Answer": "A force which opposes the motion of an object."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 397,
    "Question": "What is meant by drag?",
    "Answer": "A force which opposes the motion of an object in a fluid."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 398,
    "Question": "In what direction does a frictional force act?",
    "Answer": "In the opposite direction to the motion of the object."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 399,
    "Question": "In what direction does lift act, relative to a flowing fluid?",
    "Answer": "At right angles to the flowing fluid."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 400,
    "Question": "What can you say about the frictional forces and the driving forces acting on an object when it reaches terminal velocity?",
    "Answer": "They are equal and opposite (balanced)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 401,
    "Question": "Sketch a velocity-time graph for an object falling through the air and reaching terminal velocity.",
    "Answer": "Initially there is some uniform acceleration, the rate of acceleration slows as the  air resistance increases, eventually leading to a constant velocity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 402,
    "Question": "How can a skydiver reduce her terminal velocity?",
    "Answer": "Open her parachute to increase the drag force acting on her."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 403,
    "Question": "How does friction change the energy store of an object?",
    "Answer": "Converts kinetic energy into thermal energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 404,
    "Question": "Explain how air resistance affects the maximum speed of a car.",
    "Answer": "As the speed of the car increases, the air resistance acting on the car also increases, until these forces are balanced and the car is travelling at it's top speed. The force of air resistance limits the maximum speed of the car. A larger air resistance will mean a slower top speed, a smaller force of air resistance means a higher top speed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 405,
    "Question": "Other than increasing the power of the engine, how could the maximum speed of the car be increased?",
    "Answer": "Make the body of the car more aerodynamic to reduce air resistance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 406,
    "Question": "What affect does speed have on air resistance?",
    "Answer": "Air resistance increases as speed increases."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 407,
    "Question": "How can frictional forces acting on an object be reduced?",
    "Answer": "By making the object more streamlined."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 408,
    "Question": "What does the acceleration-time graph look like for a parachutist falling and reaching terminal velocity?",
    "Answer": "Acceleration starts at 9.81 ms-2 and reduces in a non-uniform way until reaching 0 ms-2 where the parachutist reaches terminal velocity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 409,
    "Question": "What is the initial rate of acceleration on earth? Why does it decrease as the object falls?",
    "Answer": "9.81 ms-2. Air resistance increases reducing the resultant force."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 410,
    "Question": "Why does a kicked football move in a parabolic curve/projectile motion",
    "Answer": "Because the horizontal velocity remains constant, while the vertical velocity is affected by acceleration downwards due to gravity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 411,
    "Question": "When looking at projectile motion questions, how should you treat the horizonal and vertical components of motion?",
    "Answer": "Horizontal and vertical components of motion should be treated independently."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "SUVAT and Projectile Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 2,
    "No.": 412,
    "Question": "Define terminal velocity",
    "Answer": "The maximum velocity an object will fall at when the force of weight is balanced by the force of air resistance"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 413,
    "Question": "What is a contact force?",
    "Answer": "A force between two object which are touching"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 414,
    "Question": "What is a non-contact force?",
    "Answer": "A force between objects which are separated by space."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 415,
    "Question": "Give two examples of contact forces",
    "Answer": "e.g. friction, air resistance, tension, drag, reaction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 416,
    "Question": "List three non-contact forces",
    "Answer": "gravitational, electrostatic, magnetic"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 417,
    "Question": "If a body is in equilibrium, what is the sum of all the forces acting on it?",
    "Answer": "0 N"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 418,
    "Question": "Explain what equilibrium means in the context of a moving object.",
    "Answer": "Equilibrium means that the moving object will have no resultant force acting on it so it will be moving at a constant speed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 419,
    "Question": "Define weight",
    "Answer": "The force of gravity acting on an object's mass"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 420,
    "Question": "Give the formula which links Weight, mass and gravitational field strength",
    "Answer": "W = mg"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 421,
    "Question": "What is the value of g on earth?",
    "Answer": "9.81 ms-^2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 422,
    "Question": "State Newton's first law of motion",
    "Answer": "If there is no resultant force acting on an object it will either stay at rest or move with a constant speed in the same direction."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 423,
    "Question": "State Newtons second law of motion",
    "Answer": "If there is a resultant force acting on an object it will accelerate in the direction of the resultant force. The acceleration of an object is proportional to the resultant force acting on it."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 424,
    "Question": "State Newtons third law",
    "Answer": "If object A exerts a force on object B, object B will exert and equal force on A but in the opposite direction."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 425,
    "Question": "Explain with reference to Newton's third law how we are able to walk across the floor.",
    "Answer": "In order to walk across the floor, you must push back on the floor with your foot; then, according to Newton's Third Law, the floor pushes forward on your foot, which propels you forward. This, of course, requires friction to work."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 426,
    "Question": "Explain why the equal and opposite force of a books weight on the table is not the reaction force of the table acting on the book.",
    "Answer": "The forces are acting on the same object but the forces are of different types."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 427,
    "Question": "Name the equal and opposite force of a book's reaction force on a table according to Newton's third law.",
    "Answer": "The reaction force of the table acting on the book."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 428,
    "Question": "How much resultant force is needed to accelerate a 24.1 kg mass by 3.5 ms^-2?",
    "Answer": "84 N (2.s.f)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 429,
    "Question": "A resultant force of 18 N is applied to a toy car with a mass of 0.61 kg. What will the magnitude of the car's acceleration be?",
    "Answer": "30 ms-2 (2.s.f)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 430,
    "Question": "Two ice skaters of mass 55.0 kg and 60.0 kg push against each other. The heavier ice skater accelerates away at 2.3 ms^-2. What will the magnitude of the lighter ice skaters acceleration be?",
    "Answer": "2.5 ms-2 (2.s.f)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 431,
    "Question": "Explain how a swimmer moves forwards in the water.",
    "Answer": "The swimmer pushes back against the water with their arms and legs, the water pushes the swimmer forwards with an equal sized force."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 432,
    "Question": "What are the two conditions necessary for two equal and opposite forces to obey Newton's third law?",
    "Answer": "The forces must act on different objects, they must be the same type of force."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 433,
    "Question": "Why does a bird lift into the air when it flaps its wings?",
    "Answer": "When a bird flaps its wings it pushes down on the air. The air then pushes back up o the bird's wings with the same force, which causes it to lift."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 434,
    "Question": "How can Newton's second law be written as a formula?",
    "Answer": "F = ma"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 435,
    "Question": "Give the formula for momentum, including the units for each quantity",
    "Answer": "p= mv ,  p, momentum, measured in kgms-1 , m, mass, measured in kg, v, velocity, measured in ms-1"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 436,
    "Question": "What unit is momentum measured in?",
    "Answer": "kgms-1"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 437,
    "Question": "Is momentum a vector or a scalar quantity?",
    "Answer": "Vector"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 438,
    "Question": "What two quantities does momentum depend on?",
    "Answer": "Mass and velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 439,
    "Question": "Which of the following gives a body's change in momentum? A) The gradient of a force-time graph. B) The area under a force-time graph. C) The gradient of a force-distance graph. D) The area under a force-distance graph.",
    "Answer": "B) The area under a force-time graph."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 440,
    "Question": "Moving objects with mass are said to have __________?",
    "Answer": "Momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 441,
    "Question": "State the law of conservation of momentum",
    "Answer": "In a closed system the total momentum before an event is equal to the total momentum after an event."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 442,
    "Question": "What is conserved in an elastic collision?",
    "Answer": "Kinetic energy, total energy and momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 443,
    "Question": "What is conserved in an inelastic collision?",
    "Answer": "Only momentum and total energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 444,
    "Question": "What is the formula for kinetic energy?",
    "Answer": "E = 1/2 mv2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 445,
    "Question": "How do crumple zones make cars safer?",
    "Answer": "They are designed to crumple easily, which increases the impact time, reducing the average force that is needed to stop you."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 446,
    "Question": "What is impulse?",
    "Answer": "Force x time"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 447,
    "Question": "What are the units of impulse?",
    "Answer": "Ns"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 448,
    "Question": "The impulse on a body is equal to ",
    "Answer": "The change in momentum of that body"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 449,
    "Question": "What does the area under a force-time graph give you?",
    "Answer": "Impulse"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 450,
    "Question": "How do air bags work?",
    "Answer": "The person's kinetic energy is absorbed by the air bag, the impact time is lengthened, reducing the force on the passenger."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 451,
    "Question": "How does  a seat belt work to make a passenger safer?",
    "Answer": "The seat belt stretches, increasing the time it takes you to stop, reducing the force needed to stop you."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 452,
    "Question": "As force is equal to the rate of change of momentum, how can the force acting be increased?",
    "Answer": "Decreasing the time the change in momentum takes place over."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Newton's Laws and Momentum",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 4,
    "No.": 453,
    "Question": "A squash ball moving horizontally hits a squash racquet. How would you calculate the impulse acting on the ball?",
    "Answer": "Impulse is equal to the change in momentum, so you would need to subtract the momentum before the collision from the momentum after the collision."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 454,
    "Question": "What are the units of work done?",
    "Answer": "Joules"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 455,
    "Question": "What is the formula for work done when the force and direction moved are in the same plane?",
    "Answer": "W = Fs"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 456,
    "Question": "How do you calculate work done when the direction of the movement is different from the direction of the force making it move?",
    "Answer": "Resolve the force in the direction of the motion. W =F s cos Î¸"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 457,
    "Question": "What does work mean in physics?",
    "Answer": "Work is the amount of energy transferred from one form to another when a force causes a movement of some kind."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 458,
    "Question": "What unit is power measured in?",
    "Answer": "Watts (W)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 459,
    "Question": "What is the Watt defined as?",
    "Answer": "1 Watt is one joule per second"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 460,
    "Question": "What is transferred when work is done?",
    "Answer": "Energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 461,
    "Question": "Power is the rate of doing what?",
    "Answer": "Doing work"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 462,
    "Question": "What does the area under a force-displacement graph tell you?",
    "Answer": "Work done"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 463,
    "Question": "Which equation links power and speed of a moving object?",
    "Answer": "P = W/t --> P = Fs/t --> P = Fv"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 464,
    "Question": "What does the principle of conservation of energy state?",
    "Answer": "The principle of conservation of energy states: Energy cannot be created or destroyed. Energy can be transferred from one form to another but the total amount of energy in a closed system will not change."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 465,
    "Question": "Efficiency is a measure of how well energy is __________.",
    "Answer": "Transferred."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 466,
    "Question": "When an object falls, _______ energy is transferred to ___________ energy.",
    "Answer": "When an object falls, gravitational potential energy is transferred to kinetic energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 467,
    "Question": "Why are no machines 100 % efficient?",
    "Answer": "Whenever energy is transferred, some energy is converted to less useful forms (such as heat and sound)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 468,
    "Question": "How is efficiency calculated in terms of energy?",
    "Answer": "Efficiency = useful energy output/ total input energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 469,
    "Question": "Which of the following is the correct unit for efficiency? A) joules B) watts C) seconds D) Efficiency has no units",
    "Answer": "D) Efficiency has no units"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 470,
    "Question": "How is efficiency calculated in terms of power?",
    "Answer": "Efficiency = useful power output/ total input power"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Work Energy and Power",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 6,
    "No.": 471,
    "Question": "Describe the energy transfers involved when a catapult string is drawn back and a pellet is fired out of the catapult.",
    "Answer": "Work is done by the hand to pull the catapult string back, transferring he kinetic energy of the hand to elastic potential energy is stored in the string. When the string is released the elastic potential energy is converted into kinetic energy, which is transferred to the pellet. As the pellet travels through the air the kinetic energy of the pellet is transferred to thermal energy of the surroundings."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 472,
    "Question": "What is the formula for density?",
    "Answer": "p =m/V"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 473,
    "Question": "What are the units for density?",
    "Answer": "kgm^-3"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 474,
    "Question": "What is the definition of density?",
    "Answer": "Density is the mass per unit volume"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 475,
    "Question": "What determines whether an object will float or sink on a fluid?",
    "Answer": "When the object is more dense than the fluid (it will sink) or less dense than the fluid (it will float),"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 476,
    "Question": "What does Hookes law state?",
    "Answer": "The extension of a stretched wire, is proportional to the load or force F."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 477,
    "Question": "How can Hookes law be written as a formula?",
    "Answer": "F = k l "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 478,
    "Question": "Hookes law applies to both stretched wires and stretched and compressed?",
    "Answer": "Springs"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 479,
    "Question": "The limit of proportionality is?",
    "Answer": "The point up to which Hooke's law is obeyed. Force is proportional to extension"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 480,
    "Question": "The elastic limit of a material is …?",
    "Answer": "The point after which the material will become permanently deformed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 481,
    "Question": "Elastic deformation means…?",
    "Answer": "The material will return to its original shape once the forces are removed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 482,
    "Question": "Plastic deformation means…?",
    "Answer": "The material will not return to it's original length once the forces are removed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 483,
    "Question": "If a pair of opposite forces stretch a material, they're called?",
    "Answer": "tensile forces."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 484,
    "Question": "If a pair of opposite forces compress a material, they are called?",
    "Answer": "compressive forces."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 485,
    "Question": "Tensile stress is defined as…",
    "Answer": "the force applied, F, divided by the cross-sectional area, A. Stress = F/A"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 486,
    "Question": "What are the units of tensile stress?",
    "Answer": "Nm^-2 or Pascals, Pa"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 487,
    "Question": "Tensile strain is defined as….",
    "Answer": "The change in length divided by the original length of the material."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 488,
    "Question": "What are the units of tensile strain?",
    "Answer": "No units as it is a ratio."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 489,
    "Question": "What is the breaking stress of a material?",
    "Answer": "This is the stress that is big enough to break the material."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 490,
    "Question": "What is the ultimate tensile strength stress of a material?",
    "Answer": "Ultimate tensile strength is the maximum stress that the material can withstand."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 491,
    "Question": "What is elastic strain energy?",
    "Answer": "It is the potential energy stored when a material is stretched (before the elastic limit is met)."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 492,
    "Question": "What are the units of spring constant?",
    "Answer": "N/m"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 493,
    "Question": "What does the area under a force-extension graph tell you?",
    "Answer": "The elastic strain energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 494,
    "Question": "What does the gradient of a force - extension graph tell you",
    "Answer": "spring constant k"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 495,
    "Question": "How is energy conserved as a stretched wire undergoes plastic deformation?",
    "Answer": " energy is used to move atoms in the material away from each other. This energy is dissipated as heat."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 496,
    "Question": "Describe the energy changes in a spring as it is stretched and released",
    "Answer": "When a spring is stretched, kinetic energy is transferred to elastic strain energy and stored in the spring. When the spring is released, the elastic strain energy is transferred to kinetic energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 497,
    "Question": "Name the law that says the extension of a stretched object is proportional to the force applied?",
    "Answer": "Hooke's Law"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 498,
    "Question": "State the units of Young modulus",
    "Answer": "Pa or Nm^-2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 499,
    "Question": "Define Young's modulus",
    "Answer": "The ration of stress/strain"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 500,
    "Question": "What does the area beneath a stress-strain graph represent?",
    "Answer": "Energy stored per unit volume"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 501,
    "Question": "What does the gradient of a stress-strain graph represent",
    "Answer": "Youngs modulus"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 502,
    "Question": "What is the difference between elastic deformation and plastic deformation?",
    "Answer": "If a material undergoes elastic deformation, the material will return to its original shape and size once the load is removed. Whereas, if the material undergoes plastic deformation, the material will not return to its original shape and size once the load is removed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 503,
    "Question": "True or false? The stress-strain graphs of two different sized pieces of nickel have the same gradient",
    "Answer": "True. The gradient of a stress-strain graph is equal to the Young modulus of the material. Both pieces are made from the same material, so will have the same Young modulus and therefore the same gradient."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 504,
    "Question": "Why is it better to use a longer wire when using a wire to find the Young modulus",
    "Answer": "The longer the wire, the bigger the extension for a given force. A bigger extension is easier to see and measure, and it reduces the percentage uncertainty in the measurements."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 505,
    "Question": "Define ductile",
    "Answer": "Ability to exhibit a lot of plastic deformation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 506,
    "Question": "Describe the stress-strain graph for a brittle material up to fracture.",
    "Answer": "Straight line from the origin"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 507,
    "Question": "What does the area bound by a loading and unloading curve represent?",
    "Answer": "Thermal energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Mechanics and materials",
    "Sub-topic": "Materials",
    "Specification Reference": "3.4.2",
    "Teaching Order": 8,
    "No.": 508,
    "Question": "E = 210 Gpa, m = 10 kg, l = 10 m, diameter = 2 mm What is the extension in mm?",
    "Answer": "1.5"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 509,
    "Question": "Define Electric Current",
    "Answer": "the rate of flow of electric charge"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 510,
    "Question": "Current is measured in what unit?",
    "Answer": "Amperes (Amps, A)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 511,
    "Question": "What unit is charge measured in?",
    "Answer": "Coulomb ( C )"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 512,
    "Question": "Define Potential difference",
    "Answer": "the work done when a coulomb of charge passes between two points."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 513,
    "Question": "Which direction does conventional current flow?",
    "Answer": "Positive to negative"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 514,
    "Question": "What direction do electrons flow?",
    "Answer": "Negative to positive"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 515,
    "Question": "In a circuit the potential difference causes .....?",
    "Answer": "charge to flow"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 516,
    "Question": "Define Resistance",
    "Answer": "caused by anything which opposes the flow of electric charge. The ratio of potential difference to current."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 517,
    "Question": "Particles which can be charge carries in a circuit?",
    "Answer": "electrons or ions"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 518,
    "Question": "What is a series circuit?",
    "Answer": "A circuit with only one route for charge to flow"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 519,
    "Question": "What is a parallel circuit?",
    "Answer": "A circuit with more than one route for charge to flow"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 520,
    "Question": "Are ammeters connected to a circuit in series or parallel?",
    "Answer": "Series"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 521,
    "Question": "Are Voltmeters connected to a circuit in series or parallel?",
    "Answer": "Parallel"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 522,
    "Question": "State the equation which links charge flow, current and time",
    "Answer": "Q=It"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 523,
    "Question": "State the equation which links current, potential difference and resistance",
    "Answer": "V=IR"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 524,
    "Question": "State the equation which links current, potential difference and power",
    "Answer": "P=IV"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 525,
    "Question": "State the equation which links current, power and resistance",
    "Answer": "P=I^2/R"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 526,
    "Question": "State the equation which links energy transferred, power and time",
    "Answer": "E=Pt"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 527,
    "Question": "State the equation which links charge flow, work done and power",
    "Answer": "W=QV"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 528,
    "Question": "What is the unit of charge?",
    "Answer": "Coulomb ( C )"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 529,
    "Question": "What is the unit of current?",
    "Answer": "Amps (A)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 530,
    "Question": "What is the unit for potential difference?",
    "Answer": "Volts (V)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 531,
    "Question": "What is the unit for resistance?",
    "Answer": "Ohms"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 532,
    "Question": "What is the unit for power?",
    "Answer": "Watts (W)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 533,
    "Question": "State the rule for current in a series circuit",
    "Answer": "the current is the same at every point in the circuit and in every component"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 534,
    "Question": "State the rule for potential difference in a series circuit",
    "Answer": "the total potential difference of the power supply is shared between components"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 535,
    "Question": "State the rule for current in a parallel circuit",
    "Answer": "Total current stays the same but current can split across each branch"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 536,
    "Question": "State the rule for potential difference in a parallel circuit",
    "Answer": "Sum of pd across each branch's is equal to emf across the supply since energy is conserved"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 537,
    "Question": "What is Ohms Law?",
    "Answer": "Ohms law states that provided the physical conditions, such as temperature, remain constant, the current through a ohmic conductor is directly proportional to the potential difference across it."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 538,
    "Question": "What happens to the resistance of an ohmic conductor if you double the potential difference across it?",
    "Answer": "The resistance remains constant. Ohmic conductors have a constant resistance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 539,
    "Question": "Sketch the I-V characteristics for an Ohmic conductor",
    "Answer": "Straight line through the origin."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 540,
    "Question": "Sketch the I-V characteristics for a semiconductor diode.",
    "Answer": "In the forward direction, diodes require a voltage of around 0.6V, after which the  graph slopes upwards steeply. In the reverse bias, the resistance of the diode is very high and the current that flows is very tiny."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 541,
    "Question": "Sketch the I-V characteristics for a filament lamp.",
    "Answer": "This is a curve that starts steep, but the gradient gets shallower."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 542,
    "Question": "Explain the shape of the graph for the I-V characteristics",
    "Answer": "The current through ohmic conductors is directly proportional to the voltage through the conductor. This means you get a straight line graph through the origin as resistance is constant."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 543,
    "Question": "Explain the shape of the graph for the I-V characteristics",
    "Answer": "Diodes only let current flow in one direction, so don't allow current through in the reverse bias, but current is allowed through in the forward bias."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 544,
    "Question": "Explain the shape of the graph for the I-V characteristics",
    "Answer": "For small voltages the I-V graph shows a proportional relationship between current and voltage. But at larger currents, electrical energy is transferred to heat energy and causes the metal to heat up. This causes the metal ions in the metal to vibrate more. The more vibrations, the more resistance. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 545,
    "Question": "What resistance should an ideal ammeter have? Why?",
    "Answer": "0 resistance, so the current is not affected by the instrument measuring it."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 546,
    "Question": "What resistance should an ideal voltmeter have? Why?",
    "Answer": "infinite resistance. So no current will flow through the voltmeter and affect the voltage measurement being taken."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 547,
    "Question": "Is a filament lamp an ohmic conductor? How can you tell this?",
    "Answer": "A filament lamp is not an ohmic conductor. It's characteristic I-V graph is not a straight line, so voltage is not directly proportional to current."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 548,
    "Question": "What does a materials resistivity tell you?",
    "Answer": "The resistivity of a material tells you how difficult it is for current to flow through the material."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 549,
    "Question": "What four things does the resistance of a wire depend on?",
    "Answer": "Length of the wire, cross-sectional area of the wire, the resistivity of the material, temperature"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 550,
    "Question": "How does the length of a wire affect its resistance?",
    "Answer": "The longer the wire the greater the resistance. Resistance is proportional to the length of the wire."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 551,
    "Question": "How does the cross-sectional area of a wire affect the resistance",
    "Answer": "The greater the cross-sectional area, the lower the resistance. They are inversely proportional"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 552,
    "Question": "Define resistivity.",
    "Answer": "The resistivity of a material is the resistance of a 1 m length with a 1m^2 cross-sectional area."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 553,
    "Question": "What unit is resistance measured in ?",
    "Answer": "Ohms"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 554,
    "Question": "What unit is resistivity measured in?",
    "Answer": "Ohm meters"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 555,
    "Question": "What happens to the resistance of a wire when it is heated?",
    "Answer": "When a wire is heated, the resistance increases. This is because the metal ions within the wire are vibrating faster. There will be more collisions between the electrons and the metal ions in the wire, which will make it harder for the electrons to flow."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 556,
    "Question": "If the length of a wire is doubled what will happen to its resistance?",
    "Answer": "Double"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 557,
    "Question": "If the cross sectional area of a wire is doubled what will happen to its resistance?",
    "Answer": "Decrease by a factor of 4"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 558,
    "Question": "What is a semiconductor?",
    "Answer": "A semiconductor is a material that isn't as good at conducting as metals, but if enough energy is supplied to the semiconductor it can release more charge carriers, decreasing the resistivity and allowing more current to flow."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 559,
    "Question": "What does NTC stand for?",
    "Answer": "Negative temperature coefficient"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 560,
    "Question": "Describe how the temperature of a NTC thermistor varies with temperature?",
    "Answer": "As the temperature increases the resistance decreases but with a decreasing rate."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 561,
    "Question": "Explain why the resistance of a NTC thermistor decreases as temperature increases?",
    "Answer": "The resistance decreases as the temperature of the thermistor increases because thermal energy is transferred to the electrons within the thermistor, giving them enough energy to escape from their atoms. This means there are more charge carriers and so lowers the resistance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 562,
    "Question": "Describe how the resistance of an LDR varies with light intensity",
    "Answer": "As the light intensity increases the resistance decreases at a decreasing rate."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 563,
    "Question": "Explain why the resistance of an LDR varies with light intensity",
    "Answer": "As the light intensity increases the electrons are given enough energy the be released from their atoms and therefore increases the number of charge carriers and reducing the resistivity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 564,
    "Question": "What is a superconductor?",
    "Answer": "A superconductor is a material which when cooled below a critical temperature their resistivity becomes zero."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 565,
    "Question": "Below what temperature do superconductors have zero resistivity?",
    "Answer": "The critical temperature."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 566,
    "Question": "Name three applications of super conductors",
    "Answer": "Creating strong magnetic fields, which can be used in MRI scanners, particle accelerators or Maglev trains. Use in power cables for transmitting electricity without any loss of power. Use in fast electrical circuits as no resistance to slow the current."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 567,
    "Question": "Explain how superconductors can be used to reduce energy losses?",
    "Answer": "In power transmission, energy is lossed in the wires due to resistance. If superconductors are used and the resistance is zero, then energy can be transmitted without any loss in power."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 568,
    "Question": "Give one disadvantage of using superconductors.",
    "Answer": "Maintaining conductors at or below their critical temperature (generally around 10 kelvin) is difficult and very expensive."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 569,
    "Question": "What instrument would you use to find the diameter of a wire",
    "Answer": "A micrometre"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 570,
    "Question": "What is the uncertainty when using a micrometre?",
    "Answer": "0.01 mm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 571,
    "Question": "In electricity experiments explain why it is important to keep the temperature constant",
    "Answer": "The resistivity of a material is dependent on temperature, so the temperature must be kept constant so that it doesn't affect the results of the experiment. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 572,
    "Question": "In experiments explain how to keep the current small",
    "Answer": "The temperature can be kept constant by using small currents and by including a switch in the circuit so current is only flowing whist the measurements are being taken."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 573,
    "Question": "Define the term power.",
    "Answer": "Power is the rate of transfer of energy."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 574,
    "Question": "What is one Watt equivalent to?",
    "Answer": "A Watt is equal to one joule per second."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 575,
    "Question": "Give three equations you could use to calculate electrical power?",
    "Answer": "P= IV, P = I^2/R, P = V^2/R"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 576,
    "Question": "Give an equation for energy which relates current, potential",
    "Answer": "E = IVt"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 577,
    "Question": "What does E.m.f stand for?",
    "Answer": "Electromotive force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 578,
    "Question": "What is internal resistance?",
    "Answer": "Internal resistance is the resistance within batteries."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 579,
    "Question": "What is internal resistance caused by?",
    "Answer": "Internal resistance is caused by the electrons within the battery colliding with the atoms in the battery."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 580,
    "Question": "What is e.m.f?",
    "Answer": "The electromotive force is the amount of energy produced by the battery and transferred to each coulomb of charge."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 581,
    "Question": "What unit is e.m.f measured in?",
    "Answer": "Volts (V)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 582,
    "Question": "State the formula which links e.m.f, energy and charge.",
    "Answer": "e.m.f = E/Q"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 583,
    "Question": "What is the terminal p.d?",
    "Answer": "Terminal p.d. is the potential difference across all of the components in the circuit, outside of the battery."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 584,
    "Question": "What causes batteries to warm up when they are used?",
    "Answer": "The internal resistance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 585,
    "Question": "What is the load resistance?",
    "Answer": "The total resistance of all the components in the circuit, outside of the battery."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 586,
    "Question": "The energy wasted per coulomb overcoming the internal resistance is called the?",
    "Answer": "Lost volts."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 587,
    "Question": "Give the equation which links e.m.f, current, load resistance",
    "Answer": "e = I(R+r)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 588,
    "Question": "What do the gradient and vertical intercept on a V-I graph for internal resistance represent?",
    "Answer": "The gradient shows -r, where r is the internal resistance, the y intercept shows e.m.f."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 589,
    "Question": "The total current flowing into a  junction is equal to?",
    "Answer": "The total current flowing out of that junction."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 590,
    "Question": "The total e.m.f around a series circuit = ?",
    "Answer": "The sum of the p.d.s across each component."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 591,
    "Question": "In a series circuit the total resistance is equal to?",
    "Answer": "In a series circuit the total resistance is equal to the sum of the resistance across each component in the circuit."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 592,
    "Question": "Give an equation which tells you the total resistance in a series circuit?",
    "Answer": "R = R1 +R2 +R3+…."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 593,
    "Question": "Give an equation which tells you the total resistance in a parallel circuit?",
    "Answer": "1/R = 1/R1 +1/R2 +1/R3+…"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 594,
    "Question": "What is a potential divider?",
    "Answer": "A potential divider is a circuit containing a voltage source and a couple of resistors in series. The voltage across one of the resistors is used as the output voltage. If the resistors aren't fixed, the circuit will be capable of producing a variable output voltage."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 595,
    "Question": "What are potential dividers used for?",
    "Answer": "Potential dividers can be used to supply a potential difference, V out, between zero and the total potential difference across the power supply."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 596,
    "Question": "How can you make a light sensor using a potential divider?",
    "Answer": "You can make a light sensor using a potential divider by replacing one of the resistors with an LDR."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 597,
    "Question": "How can you make a temperature sensor using a potential divider?",
    "Answer": "You can make a temperature sensor using a potential divider by replacing one of the resistors with a thermistor."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 598,
    "Question": "How can you make a volume control using a potential divider?",
    "Answer": "You can make a volume control from a potential divider by using a variable resistor in place of one of the resistors."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 599,
    "Question": "What is a potentiometer? When can it be used?",
    "Answer": "A potentiometer is a potential divider containing a variable resistor instead of two resistors in series. For example they are used in volume controls on a stereo."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 600,
    "Question": "For cells in a series circuit, how do you calculate the total emf?",
    "Answer": "The e.m.f's are added together."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 601,
    "Question": "For identical cells in a parallel circuit, what is the total emf?",
    "Answer": "For identical cells in a parallel circuit, then total e.m.f of the combination of cells is the same size as the e.m.f of each individual cells."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 602,
    "Question": "Explain why the combined resistance of two resistors in parallel is always less than either of the separate resistors?",
    "Answer": "In parallel there is less opposition to current because there is more than one path for the electrons to take."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 603,
    "Question": "Explain why two 1.5 V cells connected together in series can give an e.m.f of 3 V or 0 V?",
    "Answer": "If they are both connected in the same direction, the e.m.f.s are added together. If they are connected in opposite directions the e.m.f is zero."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 604,
    "Question": "Explain why the terminal e.m.f of a cell, supplying current  to a circuit, is always less than its e.m.f?",
    "Answer": "Because energy is wasted within the cell due to its internal resistance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 605,
    "Question": "Give one factor which can affect the resistivity of a material",
    "Answer": "Temperature"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 606,
    "Question": "What is the total resistance of two  8 ohm resistors connected in parallel?",
    "Answer": "4 ohms"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Electricity",
    "Sub-topic": "Current electricity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.5.1",
    "Teaching Order": 10,
    "No.": 607,
    "Question": "What is the total resistance of four 12 ohm resistors connected in parallel?",
    "Answer": "3 ohms"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 608,
    "Question": "Define a radian",
    "Answer": "A radian is the angle subtended by a circular arc with a length equal to the radius of the circle."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 609,
    "Question": "State the equation to calculate radians",
    "Answer": "Radian = arc length/radius"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 610,
    "Question": "How many degrees and radians is one complete cycle?",
    "Answer": "360° = 2π rad"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 611,
    "Question": "Define time period",
    "Answer": "Time period (T) is the time taken for one complete revolution. It is measured in seconds (s)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 612,
    "Question": "Define frequency",
    "Answer": "Frequency is the number of revolutions per second. It is measured in Hertz (Hz)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 613,
    "Question": "Define linear velocity",
    "Answer": "Rate of change of displacement measured in m/s"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 614,
    "Question": "Define angular velocity",
    "Answer": "Rate of change of angle, measured in rads/s. Rate of angular displacement (ω = Δθ/Δt)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 615,
    "Question": "Calculate the angular velocity of the second hand on a clock",
    "Answer": "ω = 0.105 rads⁻¹ "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 616,
    "Question": "State the relationship between linear velocity and angular velocity",
    "Answer": "linear velocity = angular velocity x radius"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 617,
    "Question": "State the direction of centripetal force",
    "Answer": "Towards the centre of the circle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 618,
    "Question": "Define centripetal force",
    "Answer": "The overall resultant force acting towards the centre of a circle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 619,
    "Question": "State the direction of linear velocity",
    "Answer": "at a tangent to the circle and always at a right angle to the centripetal force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 620,
    "Question": "What is the angle between centripetal acceleration and linear velocity",
    "Answer": "90 degrees"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 621,
    "Question": "What is the angle between centripetal force centripetal acceleration?",
    "Answer": "0 degrees"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 622,
    "Question": "What is the angle between centripetal force and linear velocity",
    "Answer": "90 degrees"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 623,
    "Question": "How can an object move at constant speed but still be accelerating?",
    "Answer": "if it is moving in a circular path it is constantly changing direction. That must means its velocity is constantly changing. A change in velocity means it is accelerating. It is always accelerating towards the centre of the circle."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 624,
    "Question": "State 3 factors that can increase the size of the centripetal force",
    "Answer": "Bigger mass, Faster velocity, Smaller radius"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 625,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for a planetary orbit",
    "Answer": "Gravity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 626,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for an electron in orbit",
    "Answer": "electrostatic attraction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 627,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for a bung on a string",
    "Answer": "Tension"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 628,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for a car cornering",
    "Answer": "friction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 629,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for a car cornering on a banked slope.",
    "Answer": "Normal reaction resolved horizontally and friction resolved horizontally"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 630,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for an airplane banking",
    "Answer": "lift resolved horizontally"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 631,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for a rollercoaster at the top of a loop the loop",
    "Answer": "Reaction + weight "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 632,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force for a rollercoaster at the bottom of a loop the loop",
    "Answer": "Reaction - weight"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 633,
    "Question": "Why is the normal reaction for a rollercoaster greater at the bottom of a loop the loop that at the top",
    "Answer": "At the top the weigh helps contribute to the centripetal force. At the bottom the reaction force has to overcome all the weight and then provide the centripetal force."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 634,
    "Question": "In the rotor/graviton ride what forces are acting",
    "Answer": "Vertical equilibrium where weight is balanced by friction. Horizontally its accelerating with normal reaction providing the centripetal force."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 635,
    "Question": "What cause the centripetal force on a pirate ship?",
    "Answer": "T - mg cos"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 636,
    "Question": "What causes the centripetal force on the swing o chairs?",
    "Answer": "Tension resolved horizontally"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 637,
    "Question": "Write an expression for the resultant force acting on an object being whirled on a string in a vertical circle when at the top of its circle.",
    "Answer": "Weight + Tension"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 638,
    "Question": "Write an expression for the resultant force acting on an object being whirled on a string in a vertical circle when at the bottom of its circle.",
    "Answer": "Tension - weight"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 639,
    "Question": "A 32.5 kg child on a merry-go-round 1.72 m from centre generates a maximum friction of 114 N. Calculate the maximum angular velocity before they fall off",
    "Answer": "ω= 1.43 rads⁻¹"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Circular Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 640,
    "Question": "How can the speed of an object performing circular motion be found?",
    "Answer": "v = 2πr/T"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 641,
    "Question": "What is the period of oscillation?",
    "Answer": "The time for one complete cycle of oscillation."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 642,
    "Question": "If a trolley is at equilibrium attached to two springs, when pushed in one direction, what will the trolley do and why?",
    "Answer": "It will accelerate toward the equilibrium point. The extended spring provides a restoring force."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 643,
    "Question": "Define a free oscillator",
    "Answer": "Oscillations where there is no periodic force acting on the system"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 644,
    "Question": "Define a forced oscillator",
    "Answer": "A system is forced to oscillate by an external periodic force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 645,
    "Question": "For an object undergoing SHM where does it have the greatest velocity?",
    "Answer": "At the equilibrium position"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 646,
    "Question": "For an object undergoing SHM where does it have zero velocity?",
    "Answer": "At the amplitude"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 647,
    "Question": "For an object undergoing SHM where does it have the greatest acceleration?",
    "Answer": "At the amplitude"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 648,
    "Question": "For an object undergoing SHM where does it have the least acceleration?",
    "Answer": "At the equilibrium point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 649,
    "Question": "For an object undergoing SHM what is the acceleration as it passes through the equilibrium positions?",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 650,
    "Question": "State the two conditions required for SHM",
    "Answer": "1. Acceleration always directed towards the equilibrium position 2. The acceleration is proportional to the displacement of the object from the equilibrium position"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 651,
    "Question": "What is the relationship between displacement and frequency for a shm oscillator?",
    "Answer": "They are independent. As displacement increases the accelerations increases. This increases the average velocity which cancels out the additional distance the oscillator needs to travel"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 652,
    "Question": "What is the relationship between mass and frequency for a shm oscillator?",
    "Answer": "As mass increases the accelerations decreases (F=ma).the lower acceleration causes a lower average velocity. This means time period will increase and from f = 1/T then frequency will decrease"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 653,
    "Question": "What is the relationship between spring constant and frequency for a shm oscillator?",
    "Answer": "As spring constant increases the resting force increases (F=ke).This causes a larger acceleration (F = ma)which means the average velocity will be greater.The will reduced the time period and increase the frequency (f = 1/T)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 654,
    "Question": "Describe the displacement against time graph for an oscillator starting at the right hand side amplitude",
    "Answer": "Sin (x)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 655,
    "Question": "Describe the velocity against time graph for an oscillator starting at the right hand side amplitude",
    "Answer": "cos (x)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 656,
    "Question": "Describe the acceleration against time graph for an oscillator starting at the right hand side amplitude",
    "Answer": "At t = 0 graph starts at largest negative acceleration "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 657,
    "Question": "What function should your calculator be in when using the displacement equation",
    "Answer": "Radians"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 658,
    "Question": "Describe the acceleration against displacement graph for a SHM oscillator",
    "Answer": "A straight line through the origin with a negative gradient"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 659,
    "Question": "What can be found from the gradient of a graph of acceleration vs displacement?",
    "Answer": "(2pif)^2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 660,
    "Question": "Describe the velocity against displacement graph for a SHM oscillator",
    "Answer": "A circle with the origin as the mid point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 661,
    "Question": "Describe the kinetic energy against displacement graph for a SHM oscillator",
    "Answer": "a n shape"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 662,
    "Question": "Describe the potential energy against displacement graph for a SHM oscillator",
    "Answer": "a u shape"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 663,
    "Question": "For a mass spring system plan a practical to prove the relationship between time period and mass",
    "Answer": "Vary the mass 8 times. Measure the time period. Keep spring constant a control variable. make the experiment more accurate by repeat readings, timing for 10 oscillations and reduce parallax errors by keeping your eye level with the start and end of an oscillation. Plot a graph of T^2  against m. Relationship is proven if the graph is a straight line through the origin."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 664,
    "Question": "For a pendulum plan a practical to prove the relationship between time period and length",
    "Answer": "Vary the length 8 times. Measure the time period. Keep mass of the pendulum bob a control variable. make the experiment more accurate by repeat reading, timing for 10 oscillations and reduce parallax errors by keeping your eye level with the start and end of an oscillation. Plot a graph of T^2 against l. Relationship is proven if the graph is a straight line through the origin."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 665,
    "Question": "What is damping?",
    "Answer": "The term used to describe the removal of energy from an oscillating system."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 666,
    "Question": "How can you tell an oscillator is being damped?",
    "Answer": "It will be losing energy so the amplitude will be decreasing"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 667,
    "Question": "What are the four levels of damping?",
    "Answer": "Light, Heavy, Critical, over damped"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 668,
    "Question": "Describe light damping of a system",
    "Answer": "The system oscillates over a long time frame before coming to rest. Energy is lost slowly. The amplitude of the oscillations follow an exponential decay envelope."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 669,
    "Question": "Describe Heavy damping",
    "Answer": "The system oscillates over a short time frame before coming to rest. Energy is lost quickly. The amplitude of the oscillations follow an exponential decay envelope."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 670,
    "Question": "Describe critical damping",
    "Answer": "The oscillating system returns to the zero position of the oscillation after one quarter of a time period. Does not affect frequency. Doesn't oscillate - it just stops when it first returns to the equilibrium position."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 671,
    "Question": "Describe over damped",
    "Answer": "The oscillating system returns to zero over an extended time frame. (No discernible oscillation)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 672,
    "Question": "Give an example of light damping",
    "Answer": "Air resistance on a pendulum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 673,
    "Question": "Give an example of heavy damping",
    "Answer": "A building in an earthquake"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 674,
    "Question": "Give an example of critical damping",
    "Answer": "Car suspension system"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 675,
    "Question": "Why does light and heavy damping take place within an exponential envelope?",
    "Answer": "At the start the oscillator has the maximum energy and maximum kinetic energy (as it passes through the mid point)As the oscillator is moving the quickest is has the largest value of air resistance. The large air resistance cause energy to be lost quickly (gradient decreases quickly)As the oscillator loses energy it slows down. This means air resistance decreases and energy is lost as a slower rate. (gradient becomes less steep)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 676,
    "Question": "What is natural frequency?",
    "Answer": "The frequency of free oscillations of an oscillating system."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 677,
    "Question": "What are forced vibrations?",
    "Answer": "Making an object oscillate at a frequency that is not it's natural frequency"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 678,
    "Question": "When does resonance occur?",
    "Answer": "When the driving force on the oscillation matches the natural frequency of the system."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 679,
    "Question": "Define resonance",
    "Answer": "Max amplitude of oscillations"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 680,
    "Question": "State three effects of increasing damping on an oscillator that is resonating",
    "Answer": "1. the amplitude of vibrations at any frequency decreases. 2 resonance occurs at a lower frequency. 3 The peak becomes flatter and broader</li></ol>"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 681,
    "Question": "State some examples where resonance is useful",
    "Answer": "Microwaves heating water molecules. An antenna receiving a radio signal. Musical instruments"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 682,
    "Question": "State some examples where resonance is a nuisance",
    "Answer": "wind causing bridges to oscillate. Buildings during an earthquake"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 683,
    "Question": "State the phase relationship between the driving force and the object that is oscillating when below resonance",
    "Answer": "Below resonance they are in phase with each other."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 684,
    "Question": "State the phase relationship between the driving force and the object that is oscillating when at resonance",
    "Answer": "At resonance the phase relationship is a 90 degree or pi/2 rad."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 685,
    "Question": "State the phase relationship between the driving force and the object that is oscillating when above",
    "Answer": "Above resonance the phase relationship is 180 degrees or pi rad."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 686,
    "Question": "Sand is placed on a surface oscillating up and down, explain why above a certain frequency, the sand loses contact with the surface (3)",
    "Answer": "When the vibrating surface accelerates down with an acceleration less than g, the sand stays in contact Above a particular frequency, the acceleration is greater than there is no contact force on the sand"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 687,
    "Question": "Which equation models the displacement of a harmonic oscillator as a function of time?",
    "Answer": "x = A cos (ωt)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 688,
    "Question": "What is the amplitude and time period for the oscillator whose displacement is represented by x(cm) = 12cos(4πt)",
    "Answer": "A=12cm, T=0.5s"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 689,
    "Question": "What is the amplitude and time period for the oscillator whose displacement is represented by x(m) = 2.4cos(πt)",
    "Answer": "A=2.4m, T=2s"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 690,
    "Question": "A 0.5 kg mass is attached to a spring where k = 200 Nm⁻¹ and displaced 2 mm. Calculate the frequency of oscillation",
    "Answer": "3.18 Hz"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 11,
    "No.": 691,
    "Question": "What is g on the Moon if a pendulum has length 62 mm and completes 20 oscillations in 24.5 s?",
    "Answer": "1.6 ms^-2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 692,
    "Question": "Define internal energy",
    "Answer": "Sum of the individual potential and kinetic energies of all molecules within the body"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 693,
    "Question": "State the first law of thermodynamics",
    "Answer": "The change of internal energy of the object is equal to the total energy transfer due to work done and heating"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 694,
    "Question": "Define specific heat capacity",
    "Answer": "The energy required to change the temperature of 1kg of the substance by 1K without changing state"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 695,
    "Question": "Describe the experiment to measure the specific heat capacity of a metal",
    "Answer": "Metal block of known mass in an insulated container. Electrical heater inserted into a hole in the metal, thermometer into another. Measure the temperature change over a given time"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 696,
    "Question": "Which measurements are used to measure specific heat capacity of a metal, and how?",
    "Answer": "Heater's current (I)Heater's pd (V)Time of heating (t)Temperature change "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 697,
    "Question": "Define molar heat capacity",
    "Answer": "The energy required to change 1 mol of gas by 1K"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 698,
    "Question": "Define heat capacity",
    "Answer": "The energy required by an entire object to change temperature by 1K"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 699,
    "Question": "Explain what is meant by specific latent heat of fusion",
    "Answer": "The energy required to change one kg of an object from liquid to solid without changing temperature"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 700,
    "Question": "Water is pumped through pipes in a hot tub, why is the temperature rise greater when the pump works at a higher speed?",
    "Answer": "The pump is doing work on the water. Work can raise the temperature of the body"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 701,
    "Question": "How do you change from Celsius into Kelvin?",
    "Answer": "Celsius Temperature + 273"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 702,
    "Question": "How can you convert from Kelvin to Celsius?",
    "Answer": "Kelvin temperature - 273"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 703,
    "Question": "What is specific latent heat?",
    "Answer": "The amount of thermal energy required to change the state of 1 kg of a substance at constant temperature"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 704,
    "Question": "What is the main property of a gas at absolute zero?",
    "Answer": "It has minimum internal energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 705,
    "Question": "Define temperature",
    "Answer": "a measure of the average kinetic energy of the particles in a system"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 706,
    "Question": "Define heat",
    "Answer": "the flow of thermal energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 707,
    "Question": "Define thermal equilibrium",
    "Answer": "when two objects are at the same temperature so there is no flow of heat."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 708,
    "Question": "What causes gas pressure?",
    "Answer": "The collisions between gas particles and the inside walls of the container"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 709,
    "Question": "State the third law of thermodynamics",
    "Answer": "the entropy of an ideal substance will be zero at absolute zero (0K)."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 710,
    "Question": "What is Avogadro's constant?",
    "Answer": "The number of atoms in exactly 12g of carbon-12 (6.02x1023)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 711,
    "Question": "What is the specific latent heat of fusion?",
    "Answer": "The energy needed to change the state a substance from solid to liquid without a change of temperature."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 712,
    "Question": "What is the specific latent heat of vaporisation?",
    "Answer": "The energy needed to change the state a substance from liquid to gas without a change of temperature."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 713,
    "Question": "Define absolute scale",
    "Answer": "Measured in K starting at absolute zero"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 714,
    "Question": "Define Sublimation",
    "Answer": "a chemical process where a solid becomes a gas without going through a liquid stage"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 715,
    "Question": "What is the difference between heat and temperature?",
    "Answer": "Heat is the flow of thermal energy as it flows from a high temperature to a low whereas temperature is a measure of the kinetic energies of the particles in a selected substance."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 716,
    "Question": "What is the specific heat capacity of water?",
    "Answer": "4200Jkg⁻¹K⁻¹"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.1",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 717,
    "Question": "Calculate the final temperature if 0.5kg of 5˚C water is added to 0.8kg of 60˚C",
    "Answer": "32˚C"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 718,
    "Question": "State Boyle's law",
    "Answer": "When a fixed mass of gas is reduced in volume by a compressing piston, the pressure inside the piston increases"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 719,
    "Question": "Explain why Boyle's law is true",
    "Answer": "Gas particles all in motion. Pressure exists from surface collisions exerting a force. Volume decreases so Collisions occur more frequently. Pressure increases"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 720,
    "Question": "State Charles' law",
    "Answer": "For a fixed mass of an ideal gas at constant pressure, its volume is directly proportional to its absolute temperature"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 721,
    "Question": "State the pressure law",
    "Answer": "For a fixed mass of an ideal gas at constant volume, its pressure is directly proportional to its absolute temperature"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 722,
    "Question": "Define Avogadro constant",
    "Answer": "The number of atoms in exactly 12g of carbon-12"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 723,
    "Question": "Define molar mass",
    "Answer": "The mass of 1 mol of the substance"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 724,
    "Question": "How is work done on a gas calculated from a pressure against volume graph?",
    "Answer": "Area under the graph"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 725,
    "Question": "What is the equation for Work Done in a Piston with a set mass of gas in?",
    "Answer": "A: W = p  V              W = Work Done     p = Pressure        V = Change in Volume"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 726,
    "Question": "What is the Second Law of Thermodynamics?",
    "Answer": "It is not possible to convert heat continuously into work, without at the same time, transferring some heat from a warm body into a cold body. the total entropy of a system can never decrease over time (temperature of an object always wants to be in equilibrium with surroundings)."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 727,
    "Question": "How do you find force from pressure?",
    "Answer": "F = p x A        F = Force       p = Pressure     A = Cross-Sectional Area"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 728,
    "Question": "What does the p-V graph look like for constant pressure (isobaric process)?",
    "Answer": "Horizontal line"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 729,
    "Question": "What does the area below a p-V graph show?",
    "Answer": "Work Done"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 730,
    "Question": "What are the rules for a cycle process?",
    "Answer": "1) For a complete cycle, U = 0  (No change in internal energy)    2) the net work done = area enclosed by the cycle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 731,
    "Question": "What are the properties of an ideal gas",
    "Answer": "1. Molecules move with random motion, 2. Molecules obey Newton's laws, 2. Molecules have same average kinetic energy, 3. There are no attractive forces between molecules, 4. Collisions between molecules are elastic, 5. Molecules are point masses (have zero volume), 6. Time taken between collisions is much greater than during collisions."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 732,
    "Question": "Define empirical",
    "Answer": "Based on observation or experience rather than theory or pure fact."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 733,
    "Question": "What equation links number of moles with total mass?",
    "Answer": "number of moles = total mass / molar mass n = m/M"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 734,
    "Question": "What equation links Avogadro's constant to the number of moles?",
    "Answer": "moles = number of particles / number of particles in 1 mole n = N/N(A)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 735,
    "Question": "How many molecules are there in 20kg of oxygen gas (O₂ molar mass = 32g)?",
    "Answer": "molar mass = 0.032kgmol⁻¹ n = 625mol N = 3.76x10²⁶"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 736,
    "Question": "What happens to pressure when volume increases at constant temperature?",
    "Answer": "Pressure decreases (inversely proportional) because there is more room so fewer collisions per second"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 737,
    "Question": "What happens to pressure when temperature increases at constant volume?",
    "Answer": "Pressure increases (directly proportional) because more particles have more kinetic energy so more collisions per second."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 738,
    "Question": "What happens to volume when temperature increases at constant pressure?",
    "Answer": "Volume increases (directly proportional) because kinetic energy of particles increases so particles move further apart"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 739,
    "Question": "T₁ = 18°C P₁ = 100kPa T₂ = 220°C Calculate P₂ if volume remains constant.",
    "Answer": "P₂ = 169.4kPa"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 740,
    "Question": "How do you find the internal energy of a gas?",
    "Answer": "U = 3/2 nRT"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 741,
    "Question": "How do you find the mean particle kinetic energy of a gas?",
    "Answer": "KE = 3/2 kT"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 742,
    "Question": "Calculate the mean kinetic energy and rms speed of a nitrogen molecule at 300K",
    "Answer": "KE = 6.21x10⁻²¹ J rms speed = 517ms⁻¹"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 743,
    "Question": "Calculate the internal energy of 3 moles of gas at 300K",
    "Answer": "U = 11.2kJ"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.2",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 744,
    "Question": "How can you calculate the work done in compressing (or expanding) a gas at constant pressure?",
    "Answer": "W = pΔV"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 745,
    "Question": "What are the five assumptions that are made for the kinetic theory equation?",
    "Answer": "Molecules are point molecules. No attractive forces between molecule. molecules move in continual random motion. All collisions are elastic. Time of collisions is negligible"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 746,
    "Question": "Use the kinetic theory of gases to explain why the pressure inside a football increases when the temperature of the air inside it rises. Assuming volume remains constant.",
    "Answer": "Molecules have a greater rms velocity. Number of collisions between molecules and inside surface of ball increases per second. pressure = F/A and F = rate of change of momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 747,
    "Question": "Describe Brownian motion",
    "Answer": "particles moving randomly due to collisions with many other small, fast particles."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 748,
    "Question": "What is meant by the term elastic collisions?",
    "Answer": "Both KE and momentum are conserved and total energy is constant before and after the collision"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 749,
    "Question": "Particles exert pressure on the wall of a container because?",
    "Answer": "Molecules have momentum. Momentum change at wall. Momentum change at wall leads to force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 750,
    "Question": "Why is average velocity in a container zero?",
    "Answer": "Velocity is a vector. random direction velocities cancel"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 751,
    "Question": "How do you calculate the mean square speed of gas particles from their velocity?",
    "Answer": "Square the magnitude of the velocity of each individual gas molecule and then take the average of these values."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 752,
    "Question": "How do you calculate root mean square speed of a gas?",
    "Answer": "Square the magnitude of the velocity of each individual gas molecule, take the average of these values and then take the square root."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 753,
    "Question": "Why is root mean square speed used instead of velocity?",
    "Answer": "Average velocity is zero."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 754,
    "Question": "What is N in pV = ¹/₃ N m (c)²",
    "Answer": "Number of particles"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 755,
    "Question": "What is (c)² in pV = ¹/₃ N m (c)²",
    "Answer": "Mean square speed"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 756,
    "Question": "What is ³/₂kT equal to?",
    "Answer": "The mean kinetic energy of a gas particle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 757,
    "Question": "What form is the internal energy of an ideal gas?",
    "Answer": "Purely kinetic (i.e. no potential energy)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 758,
    "Question": "Why is there no potential energy in an ideal gas?",
    "Answer": "Becuase there are no force between particles (except during collisions)."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Further mechanics and thermal physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Thermal Physics",
    "Specification Reference": "3.6.2.3",
    "Teaching Order": 12,
    "No.": 759,
    "Question": "What is ³/₂NkT equal to?",
    "Answer": "Total internal energy of an ideal gas."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 760,
    "Question": "Define a gravitational field",
    "Answer": "A field is a region in which a force may be exerted by an object."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 761,
    "Question": "What are the rules for drawing gravitational field lines?",
    "Answer": "Gravitational Field lines represent the direction of force on a mass at that point. The separation between fields lines represents their strength Field lines drawn for a single mass. Lines never cross each other."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 762,
    "Question": "Define the strength of a gravitational field (g)",
    "Answer": "The force per unit mass on a small test mass placed in the field."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 763,
    "Question": "Describe a radial field",
    "Answer": "The field lines are like the spokes of a wheel, arrows pointing towards the centre of mass."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 764,
    "Question": "What happens to g in a radial field?",
    "Answer": "Decreases with increasing distance from the massive body."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 765,
    "Question": "Describe a uniform field",
    "Answer": "Field lines are parallel and equally spaced."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 766,
    "Question": "What happens to g in a uniform field?",
    "Answer": "Magnitude and direction of g is constant."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 767,
    "Question": "State what can be calculated from a gravitational field strength vs separation graph ",
    "Answer": "Area = Gravitational potential"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 768,
    "Question": "Explain why mass of an object is constant but weight may change",
    "Answer": "Mass only depends on the number of particles present. Weight is a force which depends on gravitational field strength. Gravitational fields strength varies on every planet"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 769,
    "Question": "Define Newton's law of gravitation?",
    "Answer": "Attractive force that is proportional to the mass of each objectInversley Proportional to r^2 (r is distance between objects)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 770,
    "Question": "When using Newtons law of attraction equation why can planets be assumed to be point masses?",
    "Answer": "The diameter of a planet is much smaller than the distance between the two planets."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 771,
    "Question": "State what can be found from a graph of force vs separation",
    "Answer": "Area = work done = GPE"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 772,
    "Question": "State Kepler's first law",
    "Answer": "The orbital path of a planet around the Sun is an ellipse, not a perfect circle. The Sun lies at one of the foci of the ellipse"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 773,
    "Question": "State Kepler's second law",
    "Answer": "An imaginary line connecting the Sun to any planet sweeps out equal areas of the ellipse over equal intervals of time. KE + PE = a constant"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 774,
    "Question": "If the radius of a orbit decreases what happens to the speed, kinetic energy, potential energy and total energy?",
    "Answer": "Total energy is a constant. Total energy = kinetic + potential So potential energy decreases so Kinetic energy and speed increases"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 775,
    "Question": "If the radius of a orbit increases what happens to the speed, kinetic energy, potential energy and total energy?",
    "Answer": "Total energy is a constant. Total energy = kinetic + potential. So potential energy increases so Kinetic energy and speed decreases"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 776,
    "Question": "What is Kepler's Third Law?",
    "Answer": "The period of planet's orbit squared is proportional to the cube of the average radius of its orbit."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 777,
    "Question": "State the orbital time period for a geostationary satellite",
    "Answer": "24 hours"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 778,
    "Question": "State the criteria for a geostationary orbit",
    "Answer": "Have a time period of 24 hours. Be at a height of 36 000 km above the Earths surface, Be circular. Be equatorial (in the plane of the equator). Rotate in the same direction of the earth (west to east)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 779,
    "Question": "State some benefits of a polar (low) orbit",
    "Answer": "A cheaper launch costs, Eventually cover the whole earth as the satellite doesn't stay above the same point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 780,
    "Question": "Define gravitational potential energy",
    "Answer": "The gravitational potential energy (W) at a point in a field, is the work done to move an object from infinity to that point. It is measured in joules"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 781,
    "Question": "State the equation for gravitational potential energy",
    "Answer": "E = - GMm / r"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 782,
    "Question": "What can be found from a graph of GPE against separation.",
    "Answer": "Gradient = force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 783,
    "Question": "Define gravitational potential",
    "Answer": "Gravitational potential at a point is the work done per unit mass to move a small object from infinity to that point. It is measured in J/kg"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 784,
    "Question": "Is gravitational potential a vector or scalar?",
    "Answer": "Scalar"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 785,
    "Question": "What is the value of gravitational potential due to a planet at point infinitely far away from the centre of a planet?",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 786,
    "Question": "Why is gravitational potential always negative?",
    "Answer": "GPE is zero at infinity. The further you raise the object, the more work you do and the greater the change in GPE. GPE increase with distance but can only increase to 0 at infinity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 787,
    "Question": "What can be found from a graph of gravitational potential against separation.",
    "Answer": "Gradient = g"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 788,
    "Question": "Define potential gradient (gravitational)",
    "Answer": "Potential gradient at a point in a gravitational field is the change in potential per metre at that point."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 789,
    "Question": "How are gravitational potential and gravitational potential energy related?",
    "Answer": "V = W/m. Potential is the work done per unit mass."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 790,
    "Question": "What are equipotentials?",
    "Answer": "surfaces that join up points of equal potential."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 791,
    "Question": "Describe the lines of equipotential in a uniform field.",
    "Answer": "They are horizontal lines, perpendicular to the gravitational field lines. They are evenly spaced."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 792,
    "Question": "Describe the lines of equipotential in a uniform field.",
    "Answer": "Circular rings around the planet. Spacing of lines of equipotential increases as separation increases"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 793,
    "Question": "Is work done when a mass moves along a line of equipotential?",
    "Answer": "No as no change in potential "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 794,
    "Question": "What is shown when lines of equipotential are close together?",
    "Answer": "If the equipotentials are close together, a lot of work must be done over a relatively short distance to move a mass from one point to another against the field  i.e. the field is very strong."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 795,
    "Question": "Why does the spacing between lines of equipotential increase as the separation from the planet increases?",
    "Answer": "This shows that the potential changes more rapidly for changes in height near the Earth than for changes of height a long distance away from the Earth. Potential gradient = gravitational field strength, g."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 796,
    "Question": "State the direction between lines of equipotential and gravitational field lines",
    "Answer": "Lines of equipotential must be at right angles to gravitational field lines. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 797,
    "Question": "State the direction of gravitational field lines in comparison to lines of equipotential ",
    "Answer": "The arrow on gravitational field lines points towards the centre of mass so in the direction of increasing potential."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 798,
    "Question": "Define escape velocity",
    "Answer": "The minimum velocity an object must be given to escape from the planet when projected vertically from the surface. For this to happen, the kinetic energy of the mass must be equal to the GPE gained"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 799,
    "Question": "How can you derive the escape velocity equation?",
    "Answer": "Initial Kinetic energy = gain in GPE. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 800,
    "Question": "State the equation for escape velocity",
    "Answer": "v = (2GM/r)^½"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 801,
    "Question": "State two reasons why rockets launched from Earth do not need to achieve escape velocity to reach their orbit?",
    "Answer": "Energy continually added in flight by thrust provided by fuel. Less energy is need to achieve orbit rather than escaping Earth's gravitational field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 802,
    "Question": "Why is the total energy supplied by a fuel to launch a satellite greater than the change in potential energy of the satellite?",
    "Answer": "Energy lost to friction (heat) and sound, Combustion of fuel is not 100% efficient (light wasted), Satellite given KE and PE as it moves upwards, Fuel given some KE as ejected downwards, Fuel is needed to raise the height of the fuel, rocket and satellite combined."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 803,
    "Question": "Earth's mass = 6x10²⁴ kg, radius = 6.4x1^³ km, calculate the force between Earth and 60 kg mass on surface",
    "Answer": "589 N"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 804,
    "Question": "A 2kg mass is 20cm left of point P. A 3kg mass is 10cm right pf point P. Calculate the resultant gravitational field strength at P",
    "Answer": "g = 1.67x10⁻⁸ Nkg⁻¹ to the right"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 805,
    "Question": "Calculate the orbital speed of a satellite 100km above the Earth's surface. Mass of Earth=6.02x10²⁴kg Radius=6.4x10⁶m",
    "Answer": "7846 m/s"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Gravitational Fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.2",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 806,
    "Question": "Calculate the altitude of a geostationary orbit",
    "Answer": "36000 km"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 807,
    "Question": "Define a field",
    "Answer": "A field is a region in which a body can experience a non-contact force."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 808,
    "Question": "What are the rules for drawing electric field lines?",
    "Answer": " The lines should never cross. The spacing of the lines represents the strength of the field. An arrow should be drawn to show the direction of force that a positive charge would feel"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 809,
    "Question": "What is a field line (electric)?",
    "Answer": "The path a free positive test charge follows."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 810,
    "Question": "What 2 pieces of information do electric field lines give about the electric field?",
    "Answer": "Strength of field (closeness of lines) and direction of force on a positive charge (arrows)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 811,
    "Question": "Describe a field between two oppositely charged plates",
    "Answer": "Field lines run parallel, at right angles to the plates. Field lines are evenly spaced. At the edges of the field the lines are slightly curved. Inside the plates is a uniform field."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 812,
    "Question": "What kind of a field is it between two oppositely charged plates?",
    "Answer": "Uniform field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 813,
    "Question": "What is a point charge?",
    "Answer": "An expression for a charged object in a situation where distances under consideration are much greater than the size of the object."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 814,
    "Question": "Sketch the electric field around a point charge?",
    "Answer": "Radial field with arrows pointing away."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 815,
    "Question": "Sketch the field around a negative point charge",
    "Answer": "Radial field with arrows pointing towards the centre of the charge."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 816,
    "Question": "Define electric field strength at a point in the field",
    "Answer": "The force per unit positive charge.E = F/Q"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 817,
    "Question": "State what can be found from  a graph of electric field strength against separation?",
    "Answer": "Area = Electrical potential"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 818,
    "Question": "Define Coulombs law",
    "Answer": "The force of attraction or repulsion between two charges is proportional to the product of the charges and inversely proportional to the separation squared."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 819,
    "Question": "State what can be found from a graph of force against separation?",
    "Answer": "Area = work done = Electrical potential energy"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 820,
    "Question": "If two forces are in the same direction, what is the resultant electric force?",
    "Answer": "F1 + F2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 821,
    "Question": "If two forces are in opposing direction, what is the resultant electric force?",
    "Answer": "F1 - F2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 822,
    "Question": "If two forces are at right angles to each other, what is the resultant electric force?",
    "Answer": "Resolve using Pythagoras."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 823,
    "Question": "State the factors that affect the electric field strength between two parallel plates",
    "Answer": "Potential difference between the plates (directly proportional). Plate separation (inversely proportional)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 824,
    "Question": "Describe the motion of a positively charged particle moving parallel to a uniform electric field.",
    "Answer": "Uniform acceleration due to uniform field."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 825,
    "Question": "Describe the motion of a positive charged particle moving perpendicular to a uniform electric field. ",
    "Answer": "Motion perpendicular to the field - constant velocity. Motion parallel to the field - constant acceleration. This causes the particle to move in a parabolic curve. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 826,
    "Question": "Define electric potential difference",
    "Answer": "The total work done to bring a positively charged particle from infinity to a separation r"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 827,
    "Question": "State the equation for electrical potential difference.",
    "Answer": "E = kQq / r"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 828,
    "Question": "For electrical potential difference against separation for two positive  charges, is potential a positive or negative value?",
    "Answer": "Positive values -  like charges repel so work is done to bring them together. There is 0 electrical potential difference at infinity. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 829,
    "Question": "State what can be found from a  graph for electrical potential difference against separation.",
    "Answer": "Gradient = force "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 830,
    "Question": "For the graph of electrical potential difference against separation for opposite charges. Is potential positive or negative?",
    "Answer": "Negative - Opposite charges attract so work is done moving them apart. There is 0 electrical potential difference at infinity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 831,
    "Question": "Define electric potential at a point in an electric field",
    "Answer": "Work done per unit positive charge on a positive test charge when it is moved from infinity to that point.V = W/Q"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 832,
    "Question": "What can be found from a graph of electric potential against separation?",
    "Answer": "Gradient = Electric field strength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 833,
    "Question": "What do lines of equipotential show?",
    "Answer": "Lines along which electric potential is constant. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 834,
    "Question": "What do closer lines of equipotential show?",
    "Answer": "Closer equipotentials means greater potential gradient at right angles to them. More work is needed to move a charged particle a set distance"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 835,
    "Question": "How is potential gradient (spacing of lines of equipotential) effected if the field is uniform?",
    "Answer": "Equipotentials between the plates are equally spaced parallel to the plates. Potential gradient is constant."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 836,
    "Question": "Describe the lines of equipotential for a uniform field between two parallel plates",
    "Answer": "Lines of equipotential are perpendicular to the electric field and are evenly spaced."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 837,
    "Question": "Describe the lines of equipotential for a radial field from a point charge",
    "Answer": "Lines of equipotential are circular rings around the charge. The spacing increases as distance from the charge increases."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 838,
    "Question": "State some similarities between E fields and g",
    "Answer": "Both have infinite range, Both follow the inverse square law with separation."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 839,
    "Question": "State some differences between E fields and g",
    "Answer": "E depends on charges but g depends on mass, E can cause attraction or repulsion. g can only attract."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 840,
    "Question": "State the direction between lines of equipotential and electric field lines",
    "Answer": "Lines of equipotential must be at right angles to gravitational field lines. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 841,
    "Question": "What is permittivity?",
    "Answer": "How well a material allows an electric field to pass through it"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 842,
    "Question": "What is the force between charges Q₁ = +5μC and Q₂ = -2.5μC separated by 1cm?",
    "Answer": "F = - 1125N (attractive)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 843,
    "Question": "What happens to the repulsive force between 2 positive charges if their separation is halved?",
    "Answer": "Force increases by a factor of 4"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Electric fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.3",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 844,
    "Question": "What happens to the potential  between 2 positive charges if their separation is halved?",
    "Answer": "Potentials increases by a factor of a 2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 845,
    "Question": "What is a capacitor?",
    "Answer": "A device designed to store charge."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 846,
    "Question": "How does a capacitor charge?",
    "Answer": "Two parallel metal plates placed near each other. When connected to a battery, electrons move through the battery and are forced onto one of the plates. This makes the first plate become negative. On the other plate, an equal number of electrons are repelled making that plate positive."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 847,
    "Question": "What is the symbol for a capacitor in a circuit?",
    "Answer": "Two equal length parallel lines."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 848,
    "Question": "What would a charge against pd graph for a capacitor look like?",
    "Answer": "A straight proportional line passing through the origin. Area = work done = energy stored. gradient = capacitance"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 849,
    "Question": "What can be found from the area  of a charge against pd graph",
    "Answer": "Area = work done = energy stored."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 850,
    "Question": "What can be found from the gradient  of a charge against pd graph",
    "Answer": "gradient = capacitance"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 851,
    "Question": "Define capacitance",
    "Answer": "The charge stored per unit pd. C = Q/V"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 852,
    "Question": "Define a farad",
    "Answer": "One coulomb of charge stored per volt"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 853,
    "Question": "What factors affect the capacitance of a capacitor?",
    "Answer": "surface area of plates, Separation of plates, Dielectric"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 854,
    "Question": "Define permittivity",
    "Answer": "Permittivity is a measure of how difficult it is to generate an electric field in that medium. The higher the permittivity of the material the more charge needed to generate an electric field."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 855,
    "Question": "Define relative permittivity",
    "Answer": "Relative permittivity is the ratio of the permittivity of a material to the permittivity of free space, it is sometimes known as the dielectric constant."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 856,
    "Question": "Explain permittivity",
    "Answer": "When charged an electric field is generated between the plates. The negative ends of the polar  molecule are attracted to the positive plate and vice versa. The molecules each have their own electric field, which now opposes the applied electric field of the capacitor. This reduces the overall electric field between the plates and therefore reduced the p.d. needed to transfer a given charge to the capacitor."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 857,
    "Question": "When capacitors are placed in series how can the total capacitance be found?",
    "Answer": "1/C = 1/C1 + 1/C2 + …...."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 858,
    "Question": "When capacitors are placed in parallel how can the total capacitance be found?",
    "Answer": "C = C1 + C2 + C3 + …."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 859,
    "Question": "For a capacitor discharging sketch a graph of voltage against time.",
    "Answer": "Exponential decay"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 860,
    "Question": "For a capacitor discharging sketch a graph of charge against time. What can be found from this graph?",
    "Answer": "Exponential decay"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 861,
    "Question": "What can be found from a charge against time graph?",
    "Answer": "Gradient = current"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 862,
    "Question": "For a capacitor discharging sketch a graph of current against time. What can be found from this graph?",
    "Answer": "Exponential decay "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 863,
    "Question": "What can be found from a current against time graph?",
    "Answer": "Area = charge"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 864,
    "Question": "Explain why the rate of change of p.d. between capacitor plates decreases as the capacitor discharges?",
    "Answer": "When a capacitor is fully charged one plates is negatively charged due to the electrons it has gained. When is starts to discharge the negative electrons repel each other. Initially there are lots of electrons, lots of repulsion so electrons leave quickly. As there are now less electrons on the plate, there is less repulsion and so electrons leave the plate at a slower rate. As voltage is proportional to charge it follows the same relationship."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 865,
    "Question": "If you measure voltage and time for a capacitor discharging, what graph would you plot to obtain a straight line? What could you find from this graph?",
    "Answer": "ln V against t. Gradient = - 1/RC. Intercept = ln Vo"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 866,
    "Question": "For a capacitor charging sketch a graph of voltage against time.",
    "Answer": "Voltage increases but the rate of increase (gradient is decreasing)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 867,
    "Question": "For a capacitor charging sketch a graph of charge against time.",
    "Answer": "Voltage increases but the rate of increase (gradient is decreasing)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 868,
    "Question": "For a capacitor charging sketch a graph of current against time.",
    "Answer": "Exponential decay"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 869,
    "Question": "Explain why the rate of change of p.d. between capacitor plates decreases as the capacitor charges?",
    "Answer": "When a capacitor is uncharged it is initially easy to add electrons onto the first plate. (so charge increases quickly)As the first plate is now negative it is harder to add electrons due to the electrostatic repulsion. Electrons are now added but at a slower rate. (charge increases but at a slower rate)As voltage is proportional to charge it follows the same relationship."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 870,
    "Question": "What is the time constant of a circuit?",
    "Answer": "The rate of discharge of a capacitor. The time take for the voltage/charge/current to fall to 1/e (37%) of its original value. Time constant = RC"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 871,
    "Question": "What are the units of time constant",
    "Answer": "seconds"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 872,
    "Question": "When t=RC in a capacitor's discharge, what percentage charge remains?",
    "Answer": "37%"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 873,
    "Question": "When t=2RC in a capacitor's discharge, what percentage charge remains?",
    "Answer": "14%"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 874,
    "Question": "At what point, is a capacitor considered discharged?",
    "Answer": "When t=5RC"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 875,
    "Question": "How can you prove a graph is exponential?",
    "Answer": "An exponential graph always shows a constant ratio property. This means in equal amount of time the Y axis will always decrease by the same ratio."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 876,
    "Question": "A parallel plate capacitor with separation 1.5mm has a capacitance of 3nF and a dielectric of relative permittivity 2.8. Calculate the area of the plates",
    "Answer": "A = 0.18m²"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 877,
    "Question": "What happens to the energy stored by a capacitor if the pd across it triples?",
    "Answer": "Increases by a factor of 9"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 878,
    "Question": "A capacitor is charged using a constant current of 2mA. Calculate the charge stored after 20s",
    "Answer": "40mC"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 879,
    "Question": "A capacitor of capacitance 400μF is charged using a constant current of 2A. Calculate the pf across the capacitor after 20s",
    "Answer": "100V"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 880,
    "Question": "What charge remains in a 250μF capacitor when charged by a 6V cell after one time constant",
    "Answer": "0.56mC"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Capacitance",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.4",
    "Teaching Order": 13,
    "No.": 881,
    "Question": "How much potential difference has built up after one time constant when charging a capacitor?",
    "Answer": "0.63 OR 63% of max"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 882,
    "Question": "What are the rules for drawing magnetic field lines?",
    "Answer": "The lines should never cross. The spacing of the lines represents the strength of the field. An arrow should be drawn to show the direction of force that a North Pole would feel"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 883,
    "Question": "Describe the magnetic field pattern around a bar magnet",
    "Answer": "Fields lines are closer at the poles and flow from north to south"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 884,
    "Question": "Describe the field lines around a straight conductor",
    "Answer": "Circular rings"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 885,
    "Question": "Describe the right hand curl rule",
    "Answer": "Magnetic fields around a straight conductor are concentric circles. Curl you right hand into a fist and point your thumb in the direction of the current. Your fingers will curl in the direction of the magnetic field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 886,
    "Question": "Describe a solenoid",
    "Answer": "A wire wrapped into a coil"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 887,
    "Question": "Describe the magnetic field produced by a solenoid",
    "Answer": "Inside the coil its a strong and uniform field. Outside the field is similar to a bar magnet"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 888,
    "Question": "How can you turn a solenoid into an electromagnet?",
    "Answer": "Adding an iron nail"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 889,
    "Question": "Describe the motor effect",
    "Answer": "A current carrying wire produces a magnetic field field. If this wire is placed near a permanent magnet, then the two fields will either attract or repel each other, exerting a force on each other."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 890,
    "Question": "Describe three ways to increase the size of the force experienced with the motor effect",
    "Answer": "larger current, Stronger magnets, Longer length of wire in the magnetic field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 891,
    "Question": "Describe two ways the direction of the force in the motor effect can be reversed?",
    "Answer": "Reversing the direction of the current, Reversing the poles of the magnets"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 892,
    "Question": "Describe Fleming's left hand rule",
    "Answer": "Thumb, first finger and second finger are placed at right angles to each other. Thumb - Motion. First Finger - direction of magnetic field (North to south)second finger - direction of current (positive to negative)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 893,
    "Question": "What are the units of magnetic flux density?",
    "Answer": "Tesla (T)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 894,
    "Question": "Define magnetic flux density",
    "Answer": "The force on one meter of wire carrying a current of one amp at right angles to the field(B = F/IL)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 895,
    "Question": "Define the tesla",
    "Answer": "1 tesla = 1 N/Am"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 896,
    "Question": "What is the unit of magnetic flux",
    "Answer": "Webers (Wb)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 897,
    "Question": "Describe how the motor effect causes a motor to rotate",
    "Answer": "Current flows into the coil and creates a magnetic field. This magnetic field interacts with the permanent magnetic field creating a force. The current flows out the coil. As the current has changed directions the force changes direction. As each side of the motor has a force in opposite directions it rotates. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 898,
    "Question": "In the motor effect what force does the wire feel when it is parallel to the magnetic field?",
    "Answer": "0"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 899,
    "Question": "Describe a charged particles motion when it travel through a magnetic field that's at a right angle to its motion?",
    "Answer": "Flemings LHR shows that a particles velocity and force are always perpendicular  to each other. This means that a charged particles will always move in a circular path. The particle will have a constant speed in a magnetic field but will always be accelerating towards the centre of the circle."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 900,
    "Question": "If a proton and electron move through the same magnetic field at the same velocity and at right angles to it which particle's path has the larger radius?",
    "Answer": "Proton (since it has greater mass)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 901,
    "Question": "Derive an equation for the radius of the circular path followed by a charged particle in a magnetic field by considering the nature of the centripetal force.",
    "Answer": "r = mv/Bq"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 902,
    "Question": "Electron has v=3.7x10⁷ms⁻¹ in field B=0.47mT at right angle. What is the radius of the path in B field?",
    "Answer": "r = 0.45m"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 903,
    "Question": "Why is the frequency of rotation independent of velocity?",
    "Answer": "If a particles speed increases it will follow a circular path with a larger radius so the time period and frequency remain constant"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 904,
    "Question": "Derive an equation for the frequency of the circular motion of charged particles in a cyclotron.",
    "Answer": "f = Bq/2πm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 905,
    "Question": "What is a velocity selector?",
    "Answer": "A velocity selector uses both electric and magnetic fields to select particles at a particular velocity. Only particles with a specific speed will the deflection by the electric and magnetic fields cancel so they travel in a straight line."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 906,
    "Question": "Describe the structure of a cyclotron",
    "Answer": "A cyclotron is made up of two hollow semi-circular electrodes with a uniform magnetic field applied perpendicular to the plane of the electrodes. An alternating p.d. is applied between the electrodes."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 907,
    "Question": "Describe how a cyclotron works",
    "Answer": "A magnetic field is applied at right angles to the dees, which accelerates particles into a semi circular path until they reach the gap. An alternating voltage is applied between the dees to produce an electric field to accelerate the particles. The frequency of the electric field must reverse polarity as particles reach the gap each time. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 908,
    "Question": "What is the difference between flux density and flux?",
    "Answer": "Magnetic flux density, B is a measure of the strength of a magnetic field. (number of field lines per unit area)The magnetic flux, passing through an area, perpendicular to the magnetic field is define as (the total number of field lines)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 909,
    "Question": "Describe electromagnetic induction",
    "Answer": "If there is relative motion between a conductor and a magnetic field, the free electrons will experience a force (F = BQv), which causes them to move to one end of the conductor. This induces an electromotive force (e.m.f.) across the ends of the conductor. If the coil is part of a complete circuit then an induced current will flow through it."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 910,
    "Question": "What is required for magnetic induction?",
    "Answer": "A conductor, Movement, A magnetic field, >A complete circuit"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 911,
    "Question": "How can you increase the size of a current induced in a straight wire moving through a magnetic field?",
    "Answer": "Move wire (or magnet) faster, Use longer length of wire, Increase magnetic field strength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 912,
    "Question": "How can you calculate the induced e.m.f. in a straight conductor moving through a magnetic field?",
    "Answer": "e.m.f. = Blv"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 913,
    "Question": "State Faradays law",
    "Answer": "The induced e.m.f. is directly proportional to the rate of the change of flux linkage. Magnitude of the induced e.m.f. = rate of change of flux linkage"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 914,
    "Question": "State Lenz's law",
    "Answer": "the direction of the induced e.m.f. or current is always such as to oppose the change producing it"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 915,
    "Question": "What EMF is induced in a straight conductor of length 5cm moving at 2ms⁻¹ perpendicular to a magnetic field of strength 0.02T?",
    "Answer": "0.002V"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 916,
    "Question": "Sketch a graph of flux linkage against time for a coil rotating in a magnetic field.",
    "Answer": "Maximum flux linkage when the coil is perpendicular to the magnetic field. Zero flux linkage when the coil is parallel to the magnetic field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 917,
    "Question": "Sketch a graph of induced emf against time for a coil rotating in a magnetic field.",
    "Answer": "Zero emf when the coil is perpendicular to the magnetic field. Maximum emf when the coil is parallel to the magnetic field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 918,
    "Question": "How can emf induced be found from a graph of flux linkage against time?",
    "Answer": "Gradient"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 919,
    "Question": "If a coil that was rotating in a magnetic field had its speed doubled how would the flux linkage against time graph change",
    "Answer": "flux linkage stays the same but frequency doubles. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 920,
    "Question": "If a coil that was rotating in a magnetic field had its speed doubled how would the emf against time graph change",
    "Answer": "emf doubles and frequency doubles"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 921,
    "Question": "Which equation is used to calculate the instantaneous EMF induced in an alternator at any time, t?",
    "Answer": "ε = BANωsinωt"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 922,
    "Question": "What is the max EMF induced in a 200 turn coil with area 2cm² rotating with a Time period of 0.1s in a magnetic field of 0.05T?",
    "Answer": "0.13V"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 923,
    "Question": "Why would a pendulum bob that swings through a magnetic field be heavily damped?",
    "Answer": "Pendulum bob cuts through magnetic field which induces a voltage across metal bob. Currents circulate in bob (eddy currents). Current produced a magnetic field. Current will always produce a magnetic field that apposes the motion that created it `This is known as Lenz's law. Magnetic fields (from current and permanent magnets) interact and dampen motion"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 924,
    "Question": "How could you compare a 2V dc battery and a 2V ac supply?",
    "Answer": "To compare them properly you need to average out the ac voltage. We can find the root mean square (rms) voltage"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 925,
    "Question": "Describe the structure of a step up transformer",
    "Answer": "An iron core with an insulated primary coil and a secondary primary coil. The secondary coil must have more turns."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 926,
    "Question": "Describe the structure of a step down transformer",
    "Answer": "An iron core with an insulated primary coil and a secondary primary coil. The secondary coil must have less turns."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 927,
    "Question": "Describe the role of a step up transformer",
    "Answer": "Increases the potential difference and decreases the current"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 928,
    "Question": "Describe the role of a step down transformer",
    "Answer": "Deceases the potential difference and increase the current"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 929,
    "Question": "Explain how a transformer works?",
    "Answer": "a.c. flows in primary coil this creates an alternating magnetic field in primary coil. Magnetic field from primary coil cuts through secondary coil via the iron core. This induces a voltage and current in the secondary coil. Current in secondary coil is also a.c."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 930,
    "Question": "Do transformers work with ac or dc? Why",
    "Answer": "only ac. Need a changing magnetic field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 931,
    "Question": "Explain why transformers are not 100 % efficient.",
    "Answer": "induced emf in iron core which allows a current to flow which creates heat energy. Lenz's law means induced current which create a magnetic field that opposes the change. Heat is also produced by the resistance in the coils. Not all the flux from the primary coil will pass through the secondary coil. "
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 932,
    "Question": "A transformer has 200 turns on the primary and 440 turns on the secondary. If the input voltage is 24V what is the output voltage?",
    "Answer": "53 V"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 933,
    "Question": "What technique is used to avoid eddy currents being induced in the iron core of a transformer?",
    "Answer": "Iron core is laminated"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 934,
    "Question": "What technique is used to minimise the loss of flux from the primary coil to the secondary coil?",
    "Answer": "Coils are wrapped over each other"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 935,
    "Question": "How is energy loss reduced in the windings of the coils on a transformer?",
    "Answer": "Use of low resistivity metal i.e. copper"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Fields and their consequences",
    "Sub-topic": "Magnetic fields",
    "Specification Reference": "3.7.5",
    "Teaching Order": 15,
    "No.": 936,
    "Question": "What is the efficiency of a transformer that has Ip = 1.2A, Vp = 36V, Is = 2.2A, Vs = 18V",
    "Answer": "0.92"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 937,
    "Question": "What material was used as a target in Rutherford's scattering experiment?",
    "Answer": "Gold foil, a few atoms thick"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 938,
    "Question": "What was measured in Rutherford's scattering experiment?",
    "Answer": "The angle of deflection of the alpha particles."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 939,
    "Question": "What happened to most of the alpha particle in Rutherford's scattering experiment?",
    "Answer": "They passed straight through the foil (with very little scattering)."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 940,
    "Question": "What proportion of alpha particles were scattered in Rutherford's scattering experiment?",
    "Answer": "Around 1 in 2000"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 941,
    "Question": "What proportion of alpha particles were deflected by more than 90° in Rutherford's scattering experiment?",
    "Answer": "Around 1 in 10,000"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 942,
    "Question": "What was concluded due to most of the alpha particles passing straight through the gold foil Rutherford's scattering experiment?",
    "Answer": "Most of the atom is empty space with most of the mass concentrated in a small nucleus."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 943,
    "Question": "What was concluded due to some alpha particles being scattered in Rutherford's scattering experiment?",
    "Answer": "The nucleus is positively charged."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.1",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 944,
    "Question": "How did Rutherford estimate the maximum radius of the nucleus?",
    "Answer": "He equated the KE of the alpha particle to the electric potential energy at closest approach to the nucleus."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 945,
    "Question": "What is an alpha particle?",
    "Answer": "2 protons and 2 neutrons OR a helium nucleus"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 946,
    "Question": "What is the speed of gamma radiation?",
    "Answer": "3x10⁸ms⁻¹"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 947,
    "Question": "What type of nuclear radiation has the greatest rest mass?",
    "Answer": "Alpha radiation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 948,
    "Question": "What is gamma radiation?",
    "Answer": "A high energy photon (emitted by the nucleus)"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 949,
    "Question": "What is the charge of an Alpha particle?",
    "Answer": "+3.2x10⁻¹⁹C OR +2e"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 950,
    "Question": "What is the charge of a beta minus particle",
    "Answer": "-1.6x10⁻¹⁹C OR -e"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 951,
    "Question": "What type of nuclear radiation is not deflected by electric and magnetic fields?",
    "Answer": "Gamma rays"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 952,
    "Question": "What type of nuclear radiation is deflected the most by electric and magnetic fields?",
    "Answer": "Beta radiation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 953,
    "Question": "When measuring the count rate of a radioactive source what must be taken into account?",
    "Answer": "The background count rate / count rate with no source present"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 954,
    "Question": "How do you find the corrected count rate for a radioactive source from the measured count rate.",
    "Answer": "measured count rate - background count rate"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 955,
    "Question": "How far do alpha particles typically travel in air?",
    "Answer": "A few cm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 956,
    "Question": "What type of ionising radiation is stopped by a sheet of paper?",
    "Answer": "Alpha radiation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 957,
    "Question": "Why are alpha particles strongly ionising?",
    "Answer": "They have a relatively large mass and charge."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 958,
    "Question": "What is the range of beta particles in air?",
    "Answer": "Around 1m"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 959,
    "Question": "What type of radiation requires around 1-3mm of aluminium to stop it?",
    "Answer": "Beta radiation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 960,
    "Question": "What type of radiation is the least ionising?",
    "Answer": "Gamma rays"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 961,
    "Question": "Why is gamma the least ionising form of radiation?",
    "Answer": "It has no charge."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 962,
    "Question": "What thickness of lead will stop a significant proportion of gamma rays?",
    "Answer": "3-4 cm"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 963,
    "Question": "Why is ionising radiation dangerous?",
    "Answer": "It can damage living cells and DNA."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 964,
    "Question": "What procedure is routinely used to minimise the dose when handling radioactive sources in the lab?",
    "Answer": "Use tongs and hold it away from your body."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 965,
    "Question": "What are the three key steps for reducing radiation dose?",
    "Answer": "Maximise distance from source, minimise exposure time and use shielding."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 966,
    "Question": "State the inverse square law for radiation.",
    "Answer": "Intensity of gamma radiation decreases with the square of the distance from the source."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.2",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 967,
    "Question": "Why does the inverse square law not apply to alpha and beta radiation?",
    "Answer": "Their intensity decreases more rapidly with distance as they ionise the air."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 968,
    "Question": "What is the definition of half-life?",
    "Answer": "The average time taken for the number of unstable nuclei/activity of a sample to decrease by half."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 969,
    "Question": "What is meant by the random nature of decay?",
    "Answer": "For a given nucleus, you cannot predict when it will decay. For a sample, you cannot predict which nucleus will decay next."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 970,
    "Question": "Define activity and its unit.",
    "Answer": "Number of decays per second. 1 Becquerel (Bq) is 1 decay per second."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.3",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 971,
    "Question": "How do you find half-life from an activity-time graph?",
    "Answer": "Pick a pair of activities where one is half the other and look at the time between them."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 972,
    "Question": "What are N and Z in a N-Z graph?",
    "Answer": "N = nucleon number. Z = proton number."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 973,
    "Question": "Describe the shape of a N-Z graph for N < 20.",
    "Answer": "Straight line, N = Z."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 974,
    "Question": "Describe the shape of a N-Z graph for N > 20.",
    "Answer": "Diverges upwards from N = Z."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 975,
    "Question": "Explain the shape of a N-Z graph for N > 20.",
    "Answer": "Neutrons increase binding from Strong Nuclear Force without increasing repulsion from Electrostatic Interaction."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 976,
    "Question": "Why are alpha and beta decays often followed by gamma emission?",
    "Answer": "Daughter nucleus is produced in an excited state."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 977,
    "Question": "Why is electron capture followed by the emission of an x-ray photo?",
    "Answer": "Electron is captured from the inner shell leaving a \"hole\" which an outer shell electron can relax into."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 978,
    "Question": "Where are beta minus emitters found on a N-Z graph?",
    "Answer": "Above the line of stability."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 979,
    "Question": "Where are beta plus emitters found on a N-Z graph?",
    "Answer": "Below the line of stability."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.4",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 980,
    "Question": "What does meta-stable mean?",
    "Answer": "A long-lived (hours to days) nuclear energy level above the ground level, e.g., Tc-99."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 981,
    "Question": "How has the radius of the nucleus been measured?",
    "Answer": "By the diffraction of fast moving electron."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 982,
    "Question": "What is R in R = r₀A^(1/3)",
    "Answer": "The radius of the nucleus."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 983,
    "Question": "What is A in R = r₀A^(1/3)",
    "Answer": "Nucleon number."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Radioactivity",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.5",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 984,
    "Question": "How is nuclear density related to nucleon number?",
    "Answer": "It is constant."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 985,
    "Question": "What is an atomic mass unit?",
    "Answer": "One twelfth of the mass of a neutral carbon 12 atom."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 986,
    "Question": "Define the atomic mass unit",
    "Answer": "It is equal to exactly 1/12th the mass of a carbon 12 atom"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 987,
    "Question": "Define the electronvolt",
    "Answer": "The electronvolt (eV) is the energy gained when 1 electron accelerates through a p.d. of 1 volt"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 988,
    "Question": "How can you convert from eV to J?",
    "Answer": "1 eV = 1.6 x 10-19 J"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 989,
    "Question": "how can you convert from MeV to eV",
    "Answer": "1 x 10^6 eV = 1MeV"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 990,
    "Question": "Define mass defect",
    "Answer": "The difference between the mass of an atom and the mass of its individual particles is known as the Mass defect,"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 991,
    "Question": "Define binding energy",
    "Answer": "The binding energy of a nucleus is the energy that would be required to separate a nucleus into its separate constituents"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.6",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 992,
    "Question": "Define binding energy per nucleon",
    "Answer": "average energy needed to \"break off\" just one nucleon from the nucleus."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 993,
    "Question": "What is the role of fuel rods in a nuclear reactor?",
    "Answer": "Contained in the reactor core and generally made of enriched uranium. Act as fuel source of the fission reactor"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 994,
    "Question": "What is the role of the moderator in a nuclear reactor?",
    "Answer": "Usually made of carbon and also part of the reactor core. Slows down neutrons within the reactor core allowing them to fuse with the uranium and make fission reactions"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 995,
    "Question": "What is the role of the control rods in a nuclear reactor?",
    "Answer": "Made of boron, which can absorb neutrons. These can be lowered into the reactor to control the rate of fission."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 996,
    "Question": "What is the role of the coolant in a nuclear reactor?",
    "Answer": "The coolant absorbs the heat from the fission reactions. It is then used to heat up water and turn it into high pressure steam"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 997,
    "Question": "What is the role of the turbine and generator in a nuclear reactor?",
    "Answer": "The turbine is turned by the high pressure steam which, in turn, turns the generator. This generates electricity."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 998,
    "Question": "The activity of a radioactive sample decreases from 0.5Bq to 0.1 Bq in 40s. What is its half life?",
    "Answer": "17.2 s"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 999,
    "Question": "The count rate of a radioactive sample decreases from 120 counts/s to 15 counts/s in 24min. What is its half life?",
    "Answer": "8 mins"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 1000,
    "Question": "How do you calculate the binding energy in Joules?",
    "Answer": "Find the mass defect in kg then use E=mc²"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 1001,
    "Question": "Carbon-14 has a mass defect of about 0.11303u. Calculate its binding energy per nucleon in MeV",
    "Answer": "7.5 MeV"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 1002,
    "Question": "What is nuclear fusion?",
    "Answer": "2 Smaller nuclei are fused together to make larger nucleus"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 1003,
    "Question": "What is nuclear fission?",
    "Answer": "A large heavy nucleus splits into 2 smaller nuclei often producing fast moving neutrons in the process"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Nuclear Physics",
    "Sub-topic": "Energy in the Nucleus",
    "Specification Reference": "3.8.1.7",
    "Teaching Order": 14,
    "No.": 1004,
    "Question": "What is enriched uranium?",
    "Answer": "Uranium that has a higher proportion of Uranium-235 in order for it to be able to sustain a chain reaction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1005,
    "Question": "Vector",
    "Answer": "A physical quantity with magnitude and direction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1006,
    "Question": "Scalar",
    "Answer": "A physical quantity with magnitude only"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1007,
    "Question": "Moment",
    "Answer": "Force times perpendicular distance from the line of action of the force to the point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1008,
    "Question": "Principle of moments",
    "Answer": "For an object in equilibrium, the sum of the clockwise moments is equal to the sum of the anticlockwise moments about any point"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1009,
    "Question": "Couple",
    "Answer": "A pair of equal and opposite forces acting on a body, but not along the same line"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1010,
    "Question": "Velocity",
    "Answer": "Change of displacement per unit time"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1011,
    "Question": "Acceleration",
    "Answer": "Change of velocity per unit time"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1012,
    "Question": "Newton's 1st Law",
    "Answer": "An object will remain at rest or at a constant velocity unless acted on by an external resultant force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1013,
    "Question": "Newton's 2nd Law",
    "Answer": "The force is proportional to the rate of change of momentum"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1014,
    "Question": "Newton's 3rd Law",
    "Answer": "For every action there is an equal and opposite reaction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1015,
    "Question": "Equilibrium",
    "Answer": "State of an object when at rest or moving at constant velocity"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1016,
    "Question": "Density",
    "Answer": "Mass per unit volume of the substance"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1017,
    "Question": "Stress",
    "Answer": "Force per unit area of cross section in a solid perpendicular to the cross section"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1018,
    "Question": "Strain",
    "Answer": "Extension per unit length of a solid when deformed"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1019,
    "Question": "Young's Modulus",
    "Answer": "Tensile stress/strain"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1020,
    "Question": "Limit of Proportionality",
    "Answer": "The limit beyond which, when a wire or a spring is stretched, its extension is no longer proportional to the force that stretches it"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1021,
    "Question": "Plastic deformation",
    "Answer": "Deformation of a solid beyond its elastic limit, the object will not return to its original length once the force is removed."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1022,
    "Question": "Elastic limit",
    "Answer": "Point beyond which a wire is permanently stretched"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1023,
    "Question": "Hooke's Law",
    "Answer": "The extension of a spring is directly proportional to the force applied to it, up to the limit of proportionality"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1024,
    "Question": "Isotope",
    "Answer": "Atoms with the same number of protons but different numbers of neutrons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1025,
    "Question": "Conservation of energy",
    "Answer": "Energy cannot be created or destroyed, only converted from one form to another"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1026,
    "Question": "Work done",
    "Answer": "Force times distance moved in the direction of the force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1027,
    "Question": "Ductile",
    "Answer": "Material that can be drawn into threads, it can be shaped or permanently deformed without fracture"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1028,
    "Question": "Brittle",
    "Answer": "Material cannot be permanently stretched"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1029,
    "Question": "Wave",
    "Answer": "Transfer energy from A to B via a medium of transfer, without transferring the medium"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1030,
    "Question": "Standing wave",
    "Answer": "When two waves travel in opposing directions and they have the same wave speed, frequency and in general amplitude, they will superpose and form a standing wave"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1031,
    "Question": "Monochromatic",
    "Answer": "Single wavelength"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1032,
    "Question": "Coherent",
    "Answer": "No change in phase relationship"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1033,
    "Question": "Diffraction",
    "Answer": "Spreading out or bending of waves as they pass through a gap or around an obstacle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1034,
    "Question": "Emf",
    "Answer": "Describes the amount of energy that is converted from one form to electrical and placed on a unit of charge at the source"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1035,
    "Question": "Ohm's Law",
    "Answer": "The current flowing through a metallic conductor is directly proportional to the potential difference across its ends, provided the temperature remains constant"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1036,
    "Question": "Resistivity",
    "Answer": "The resistance of a piece of wire 1m in length and with a cross sectional area of 1m^2"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1037,
    "Question": "Centre of mass",
    "Answer": "The point through which a single force on the body has no turning effect"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1038,
    "Question": "Principle of conservation of linear momentum",
    "Answer": "The total linear momentum of a system of interacting bodies is constant, providing no external forces act"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1039,
    "Question": "Work function",
    "Answer": "Minimum energy to liberate electron"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1040,
    "Question": "Excitation",
    "Answer": "When an electron takes in energy from a photon or collision and goes up an energy level"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1041,
    "Question": "Ionisation",
    "Answer": "When an electron takes in enough energy to leave the atom"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1042,
    "Question": "Progressive waves",
    "Answer": "Waves that move outwards from their source"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1043,
    "Question": "Transverse waves",
    "Answer": "Each particle oscillates perpendicular to the direction of propagation to the wave"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1044,
    "Question": "Longitudinal waves",
    "Answer": "Each particle oscillates parallel to the direction of propagation to the wave"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1045,
    "Question": "Rarefied",
    "Answer": "More distance between particles than usual"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1046,
    "Question": "Compression",
    "Answer": "Particles closer together"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1047,
    "Question": "Mechanical waves",
    "Answer": "Oscillation of particles in a physical medium"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1048,
    "Question": "Refraction",
    "Answer": "Change in path of light ray caused by a change in speed"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1049,
    "Question": "Total internal reflection",
    "Answer": "The angle of incidence is greater than the critical angle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1050,
    "Question": "Diffraction",
    "Answer": "The spreading of waves when passed through a gap or round an obstacle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1051,
    "Question": "Kirchhoff's First Law",
    "Answer": "The sum of the currents leaving any junction is always equal to the sum of the currents that entered it"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1052,
    "Question": "Kirchhoff's Second Law",
    "Answer": "The sum of potential differences across components of a series circuit is equal to the emf"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1053,
    "Question": "Internal Resistance",
    "Answer": "Resistance inside a source of electrical energy; the loss of pd per unit current in the source when current passes through it"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1054,
    "Question": "Potential Divider",
    "Answer": "Two or more resistors in series connected to a source of pd"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1055,
    "Question": "Superconductor",
    "Answer": "A material that has zero electrical resistance below a critical temperature."
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1056,
    "Question": "Gravitational Field Strength",
    "Answer": "The force per unit mass acting on a small test mass placed in the field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1057,
    "Question": "Gravitational Potential",
    "Answer": "The work done to move a unit mass from infinity to that point in a gravitational field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1058,
    "Question": "Kepler's First Law",
    "Answer": "All planets move about the Sun in elliptical orbits, having the Sun as one of the foci"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1059,
    "Question": "Kepler's Second Law",
    "Answer": "A radius vector joining any planet to the sun, sweeps out equal areas in equal lengths of time"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1060,
    "Question": "Kepler's Third Law",
    "Answer": "The square of the period of a planet's orbit is proportional to the cube of the mean radius of its orbit"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1061,
    "Question": "Coulomb's Law",
    "Answer": "The magnitude of the force between two charges is proportional to the product of the charges and inversely proportional to the square of the distance between them"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1062,
    "Question": "Electric Field",
    "Answer": "Region where a charged particle will experience a force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1063,
    "Question": "Gravitational Field",
    "Answer": "The region surrounding an object in which it exerts a gravitational force on any other object"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1064,
    "Question": "Geostationary Satellite",
    "Answer": "A satellite that stays above the same point on the Earth's equator as it's period is 24 hours and has the same rotation direction"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1065,
    "Question": "Electric Field Strength",
    "Answer": "Force per unit charge acting on a small positive test charge at a point in the field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1066,
    "Question": "Electric Potential",
    "Answer": "Work done per unit positive charge moving a small positive charge from infinity to that point in the field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1067,
    "Question": "Field",
    "Answer": "A region around an object where a force is exerted"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1068,
    "Question": "Capacitance",
    "Answer": "The charge stored per unit pd of a capacitor"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1069,
    "Question": "Dielectric",
    "Answer": "Material that increases the capacity of a parallel-plate capacitor to store charge  when placed between the plates of the capacitor"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1070,
    "Question": "Activity",
    "Answer": "The number of unstable radioactive nuclei that decay per second"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1071,
    "Question": "Metastable State",
    "Answer": "An excited state of the nuclei of an isotope that last long enough after Î± or Î² emission for the isotope to be separated from the parent isotope"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1072,
    "Question": "Atomic Mass Unit",
    "Answer": "One twelfth of the mass of a carbon-12 atom"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1073,
    "Question": "Mass Defect",
    "Answer": "Mass of separated nucleons minus mass of nucleus"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1074,
    "Question": "Binding Energy",
    "Answer": "The work that must be done to separate a nucleus into its constituent nucleons"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1075,
    "Question": "Critical Mass",
    "Answer": "The minimum mass required to sustain a chain reaction of fission in a nuclear reactor"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1076,
    "Question": "Fuel Rods (Nuclear Reactor)",
    "Answer": "Contains enriched uranium. Increased % of U-235 compared to uranium ore it's extracted from"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1077,
    "Question": "Control Rods (Nuclear Reactor)",
    "Answer": "Made of cadmium or boron to absorb neutrons Lifted in and out of the reactor to control the number of neutrons present and the rate of fission"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1078,
    "Question": "Moderator (Nuclear Reactor)",
    "Answer": "Made of graphite or water Slows down fission neutrons into one thermal energies, to increase the likelihood of absorption by U-235 nuclei"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1079,
    "Question": "Coolant (Nuclear Reactor)",
    "Answer": "Water flows around the core, transferring heat away from the fuel, to be used to produce steam to drive a turbine"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1080,
    "Question": "Angular Displacement",
    "Answer": "The angle moved through relative to a specific axis"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1081,
    "Question": "Angular Velocity",
    "Answer": "The rate of change of angular displacement with respect to time"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1082,
    "Question": "Centripetal Force",
    "Answer": "The force that makes an object move in a circle"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1083,
    "Question": "Simple Harmonic Motion",
    "Answer": "Acceleration is proportional to the displacement of the object from equilibrium and is always directed towards the equilibrium position"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1084,
    "Question": "Natural Frequency",
    "Answer": "The frequency of free oscillations of an oscillating system"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1085,
    "Question": "Free Vibrations",
    "Answer": "Vibrations where there is no damping and no periodic force acting on the system, so the amplitude of the oscillations is constant"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1086,
    "Question": "Forced Vibrations",
    "Answer": "Vibrations of a system subjected to an external periodic force"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1087,
    "Question": "Resonance",
    "Answer": "The driving force matches the natural frequency of the system, leading to an increased amplitude of oscillation"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1088,
    "Question": "Damping",
    "Answer": "The removal of energy from an oscillating system"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1089,
    "Question": "Magnetic Flux Density",
    "Answer": "The magnetic force per unit length per unit current on a current carrying conductor at right angles to the field lines"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1090,
    "Question": "Electromagnetic Induction",
    "Answer": "The generation of an emf when the magnetic flux linkage through a coil changes or a conductor cuts across magnetic field lines"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1091,
    "Question": "Lenz's Law",
    "Answer": "The direction of the induced emf is always such as to oppose the change that causes the emf"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1092,
    "Question": "Hall Probe",
    "Answer": "A device used to measure magnetic flux density"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1093,
    "Question": "Magnetic Flux",
    "Answer": "The product of magnetic flux density and the area perpendicular to the field"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1094,
    "Question": "Magnetic Flux Linkage",
    "Answer": "A measure of the magnetic flux of a coil of wire"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1095,
    "Question": "Faraday's Law of Electromagnetic Induction",
    "Answer": "The induced emf in a circuit is equal to the rate of change of magnetic flux linkage through the circuit"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1096,
    "Question": "Eddy Current",
    "Answer": "Induced currents in the metal parts of machines"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1097,
    "Question": "Internal Energy",
    "Answer": "Sum of Ep and Ek of molecules within the body"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1098,
    "Question": "Boyle's Law",
    "Answer": "When a fixed mass of gas is reduced in volume by a compressing piston, the pressure inside the piston increases"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1099,
    "Question": "Charles' Law",
    "Answer": "For the fixed mass of an ideal gas at constant pressure, its volume is directly proportional to its absolute temperature"
  },
  {
    "Topic": "Definitions",
    "Sub-topic": "Definitions",
    "Specification Reference": "",
    "Teaching Order": 16,
    "No.": 1100,
    "Question": "Ideal Gas",
    "Answer": "A gas under conditions such that it obeys Boyle's Law"
  }
]
